<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<csw:GetRecordsResponse xmlns:csw="http://www.opengis.net/cat/csw/2.0.2" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.opengis.net/cat/csw/2.0.2 http://schemas.opengis.net/csw/2.0.2/CSW-discovery.xsd">
  <csw:SearchStatus timestamp="2019-08-16T14:54:32" />
  <csw:SearchResults numberOfRecordsMatched="208" numberOfRecordsReturned="208" elementSet="summary" nextRecord="0">
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8f8a9aa2-528b-4494-ab88-74633dfcf446</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Protected Areas</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Land cover</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Protected sites</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>protected area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural areas protection</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-04-13</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset on marine and coastal protected areas in the EU was created in 2014 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network. The dataset is entirely based on the European Environmental Agency's (EEA) datasets "Natura 2000" and "Nationally designated areas (CDDA)". Natura 2000 is an ecological network composed of sites designated under the Birds Directive (Special Protection Areas, SPAs) and the Habitats Directive (Sites of Community Importance, SCIs, and Special Areas of Conservation, SACs). The Common Database on Designated Areas (CDDA) is more commonly known as Nationally designated areas. The inventory began in 1995 under the CORINE programme of the European Commission. It is now one of the agreed Eionet priority data flows maintained by EEA with support from the European Topic Centre on Biological Diversity. It is a result of an annual data flow through Eionet countries. The EEA publishes the dataset and makes it available to the World Database of Protected Areas (WDPA). The CDDA data can also be queried online in the European Nature Information System (EUNIS). Both EEA's datasets have been filtered by Cogea to show only maritime areas and sites (i.e. areas entirely at sea), and coastal areas and sites(internal areas that intersect and/or are tangent, using 1 km buffer, to the marine regions and subregions geographic boundaries shapefile, available at https://www.eea.europa.eu/data-and-maps/data/msfd-regions-and-subregions). The CDDA dataset cover the whole EU in the case of Natura 2000 data. In the case of CDDA, geographical coverage of GIS vector boundary data is: Albania, Austria, Belgium, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Bulgaria, Croatia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Kosovo under UNSC Resolution 1244/99, Latvia, Liechtenstein, Lithuania, Luxembourg, the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, Malta, Montenegro, the Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Serbia, Slovakia, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland and United Kingdom. For further information please visit EEA's website. Compared with the previous version, this version of includes: update to 'CDDA v14' and 'Natura 2000 End 2016', both published by the EEA in 2017; new fields have been added to CDDA, reporting the lowest possible level code of the Nomenclature of Territorial Units for Statistics (NUTS1, NUTS2 or NUTS3) in which the geographical entity is located, the percentage of the total area of marine ecosystems in the site, the major ecosystem type, additional notes about sites; new fields have beed added to Natura 2000 with area of site (ha), and the percentage of the site considered marine.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>1cf5882d-4feb-4cf7-9eb5-6a542af72773</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities, Environment, CDDA</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Land cover</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Protected sites</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>protected area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural areas protection</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-04-30</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The Common Database on Designated Areas (CDDA) was created in 2014 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network. It is entirely based on GIS Data from the European Environmental Agency's (EEA), plus selected EEA tabular data joined to the feature attributes, as well as a calculation by Cogea of marine and coastal location of features.The CDDA is commonly known as ‘Nationally designated areas’. The inventory began in 1995 under the CORINE programme of the European Commission. It is now one of the agreed Eionet priority data flows maintained by the EEA with support from the European Topic Centre on Biological Diversity. It is the result of an annual data flow through Eionet countries. The EEA publishes the dataset and makes it available to the World Database of Protected Areas (WDPA). CDDA data can also be queried online in the European Nature Information System (EUNIS).The whole dataset is available for download on the EMODnet Human Activities portal. In the webmap the EEA dataset has been filtered by Cogea to show only (i) marine areas, i.e. areas with a “marine percentage” higher than 0 and/or a marine "ecotype" (as calculated or reported by the EEA) to and (ii) areas that – even if not identified as marine by the EEA –intersect the EEA coastline or that are within a distance of 1 km from the coastline (using a 1 km inner buffer from the EEA coastline). In both cases the COAST_MAR field value=1. The EEA coastline dataset is available at https://www.eea.europa.eu/data-and-maps/data/eea-coastline-for-analysis-1.The latest version of the CDDA (version 15 from 2017) covers the entire geographical area of the 33 EEA member countries and its six cooperating countries. It includes the full geographical area under the responsibility of European countries as well as other States and Territories related to key initiatives in the European region. The resulting data covers the 39 countries as well as Greenland (Denmark) and the French Overseas Departments and Territories and Overseas Collectives. Geographical coverage of GIS vector boundary data is: Albania, Austria, Belgium, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Bulgaria, Croatia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Kosovo under UNSC Resolution 1244/99, Latvia, Liechtenstein, Lithuania, Luxembourg, the former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, Malta, Montenegro, the Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Serbia, Slovakia, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland and United Kingdom. EEA does not have permission to distribute some or all sites reported by Estonia, Ireland, Romania and Turkey.Compared with the previous version, this version includes the update 'CDDA v15', published by the EEA in 2018; a new field has been added, reporting the major ecosystem type code.For further information please visit the EEA's website.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d72b9826-9282-419d-b953-d02c66e09869</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Shellfish production areas</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Agricultural and aquaculture facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>AGRICULTURE, FORESTRY; ANIMAL HUSBANDRY; FISHERY</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fish farming</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2015-01-28</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset provides information about the location of shellfish farms. It relies on the EUROSHELL project (http://www.euroshell-net.eu/) for France, Ireland, Italy, the Netherlands and the UK (England and Wales). Euroshell data come from professional, scientific and governmental sources (Associazione Mediterranea Acquacoltori in Italy, the Sea Fisheries Protection Authority in Ireland, the Comité National de la Conchyliculture and IFREMER in France, Wageningen in the Netherlands). Data for other countries were not available in the Euroshell database so we used the lists of registered production sites under Council Directive 2006/88/EC on animal health. Points represented in the map correspond to different definitions depending on the source. They represent farm sites in Denmark, Greece, Ireland, Italy, Spain and the UK while they represent the centre of production areas for France and the Netherlands. The map provides information on main species produced, the type of data available (registered site, production areas, farms location) and whether it has been converted (areas to point) as well as the distance to the coast and the position (at sea or within the coastline -e.g. for estuaries). Additional, country-specific information is provided in complementary tables. Data for Scotland has been updated on the 17/02/2016. Other data sources are not updated on a regular basis.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d978f3dc-f028-4bde-af21-e6d707eed7e2</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities Fisheries: Monthly first sales</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Agricultural and aquaculture facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>economy</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-09-14</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on first sales of fish in the EU was created in 2016 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It originates from the data on monthly first sales of fish made available by the European Market for Fisheries and Aquaculture products (EUMOFA). EUMOFA data have been related to the fish ports locations made available in DG MARE's Master Data Register, revised when necessary according to the United Nations Code for Trade and Transport Locations database (UN/LOCODE) and according to the EUROSTAT/GISCO dataset on main ports locations. Fish species have been grouped into EUMOFA's aggregations such as Commodity Groups (CG) and Main Commercial Species (MCS). For each fish species in each place of sale, volume (net weight in kg), value (Euro) and price (Euro/kg) are provided on a monthly basis by year of reference, CG, MCS and country. The 2017 update of the dataset also includes information on fish presentation (e.g. whole, headed, gutted, etc.) and preservation state (e.g. fresh, frozen, etc.). Information on presentation and preservations state are also retrieved from EUMOFA. The geographical coverage of data is: Belgium, Germany, Denmark, Estonia, France, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania, the Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Spain, Sweden and the UK. The dataset is updated twice a year. It covers a time series from 2007 to 2017 (not complete). The EUMOFA is a fully-fledged observatory, but is also a work in progress: its coverage may be extended in the future.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>5fc6d319-0a6a-4cac-b13b-231889796e28</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Dredge dumping sites</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>dredged material</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>dumping</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>planningCadastre</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-05-20</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Shapes about dumping sites show features defined as either polygons and points in Baltic Sea, North Sea, Celtic Seas, Iberian Coast and Bay of Biscay, Macaronesia and Mediterranean Sea. Information was picked form different sources depending on the country.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>cf21ae27-20c9-4e76-81ac-d29807b8afc5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Ocean Energy Projects</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Energy resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-06-16</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on Ocean Energy projects in the EU was created in 2014 by AZTI-Tecnalia for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is updated every year, and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains points representing Ocean Energy project sites in the following countries: Belgium, Denmark, Finland, France, Ireland, Italy, Norway, Portugal, Russia, Spain, Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom. Where available, each point has the following attributes: site code (ID_1), project code (ID), name, location, country, sea basin, distance to coast (metres), resource type (wave, tidal, salinity gradient, wave/wind), starting year, ending year, lease status, technology (Based on www.aquaret.com/), device, device scale (Full scale, prototype, etc.), project scale (Commercial, Demonstrator Array, etc.), project status (operational, completed, etc.), project capacity (KW), promoter, position info (it indicates if the attribute value is original from the source or has been estimated or calcultated the polygon centroid).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a35bc5fc-f658-4e5d-aa17-2fe6cbd5bfc5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Maritime boundaries</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Maritime boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2005-08-03</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>These conventions list the coordinates of points which are the vertices of segments which, in turn, define the maritime boundaries. This layer therefore features the following elements: - The textual content of international conventions establishing maritime boundaries in Europe. Maritime boundaries featured in this layer include territorial waters, bi- or multi-lateral boundaries (e.g. in the North Sea) as well as contiguous and exclusive economic zones. Some fishing areas are also defined. - The coordinates of points listed in these conventions are vertices of maritime boundaries - The maritime boundaries themselves, defined as the segments which links the different points listed in the international conventions.This layer covers the coast and surrounding seas of EU-25 as well as the sea around Iceland and Greenland. Restrictions are those cases where no regulatory text exists within the UNCLOS till now.
Missing lines have been updated from marineregions.org even with no information about treats or regulatory text.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f313c69e-164e-43de-ba8f-b078d714da2c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities, Hydrocarbn Extraction: Active Licences</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Energy resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>energy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>hydrocarbon</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil exploration</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil extraction</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>offshore drilling</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil production (chain)</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>non-renewable energy resource</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural gas extraction</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural gas exploration</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>planningCadastre</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-07-13</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on offshore hydrocarbon licences in the EU was created in 2015 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several EU and non-EU sources. It is updated every year, and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains polygons representing active offshore hydrocarbon licences in the following countries: Croatia, Denmark, France, Germany, Ireland, Italy, Malta, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Spain and UK. Where available each polygon has the following attributes: country, code, name, type (exploration, exploitation), licensing round (it includes also pending applications in France and Spain), area (square km), area info (it indicates if the area value is original from the source or has been calculated), starting year, ending year, operator.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>234c2894-a2a3-4345-a1cb-e2dd69e1b5e7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities, Environment, Natura 2000</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Land cover</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Protected sites</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>protected area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>natural areas protection</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-04-30</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset on Natura 2000 sites was created in 2014 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network. It is entirely based on GIS Data from the European Environmental Agency's (EEA), plus selected EEA tabular data joined to the feature attributes, as well as a calculation by Cogea of marine and coastal location of features.Natura 2000 is an ecological network composed of sites designated under the Birds Directive (Special Protection Areas, SPAs) and the Habitats Directive (Sites of Community Importance, SCIs, and Special Areas of Conservation, SACs).The dataset covers the whole EU.The whole dataset is available for download on the EMODnet Human Activities portal. In the webmap the EEA dataset has been filtered by Cogea to show only (i) marine sites, i.e. sites with a “marine area percentage” higher than 0 (as calculated by the EEA) and (ii) sites that – even if not identified as marine by the EEA – intersect the EEA coastline or that are within a distance of 1 km from the coastline (using a 1 km inner buffer from the EEA coastline). In both cases the COAST_MAR field value=1. The EEA coastline dataset is available at https://www.eea.europa.eu/data-and-maps/data/eea-coastline-for-analysis-1.Compared with the previous version, this version includes the update 'Natura 2000 End 2017', by the EEA in 2018; new fields, from the EEA’s descriptive data, have been added to the Natura 2000 dataset: Organisation name, Organisation Email, Management Plan, Link to Management Plan.For further information please visit the EEA's website.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>714aeb0a-e90a-406d-9fb1-3e5cba63a492</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities_WasteDisposal_DumpedMunitions</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>dumping</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>intelligenceMilitary</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>planningCadastre</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset on dumped munitions was created by CETMAR as a result of the aggregation of data provided by several sources or reports of OSPAR commission, MED POL, Spain Ministry of Defense and Maritime Administration of Latvia. Shapes with munition dumping sites define polygons and points features in Baltic sea, North Sea, Celtic Seas, Iberian Coast and Bay of Biscay and Mediterranean Sea. Information was picked form different official sources depending on the country. Each point or polygon has the following attributes (where available): type of munition (Conventional and/or Chemical) and distance to coast (meters). The distance to coast (EEA coastline shapefile) has been calculated using the UTM WGS84 Zone projected coordinate system where data fall in.  The dataset will be updated according the availability of data and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>653ca732-4351-48cb-b3a3-740d34e2ecad</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet EMODnet Human Activities: Fish catches by FAO statistical area</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Agricultural and aquaculture facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>economy</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-04-09</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on fish catches in the EU was created in 2015 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation of EUROSTAT's fish catches datasets fish_ca_atl 27, fish_ca_atl 34, fish_ca_atl 37, fish_ca_main_h. EUROSTAT data have been related to FAO's georeferenced fishing statistical areas. Fish species have been grouped by EUMOFA's larger aggregations such as EUMOFA's Commodity Groups (CG) and Main Commercial Species (MCS). Tonnes live weight is provided for each fish species caught in EU fishing statistical area, by year of reference, fish species, CG, MCS and country. The dataset is updated yearly, as soon as new data from EUROSTAT is released. It covers a time series from 1950 to 2016. Compared with the previous version this new version includes data for 2016, as well as the new Main Commercial Species identified by the EUMOFA in 2018.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>eac1ae3d-a1ee-4f90-ac8a-1aa1ec2ba2fa</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Offshore Hydrocarbon Extraction</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Energy resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>energy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>hydrocarbon</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil exploration</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil extraction</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>offshore drilling</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil production (chain)</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>petroleum industry</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-09-04</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The database on offshore hydrocarbon extraction boreholes in the EU was created in 2014 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU (plus Norway). It is updated every year, and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains points representing offshore hydrocarbon boreholes drilled in the following countries: Croatia, Cyprus, Denmark, Faroe Islands, France, Germany, Greece (only for western coast), Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Malta, Montenegro, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Spain, and UK. Each point has the following attributes (where available): status (active, abandoned, suspended, other), country, code, name, year (spud date), purpose (exploration, exploitation, other), content (crude oil, natural gas, crude oil and natural gas, dry, other), operator, drilling company/facility, distance to coast (metres) and water depth (metres). The distance to coast (EEA coastline shapefile) has been calculated using the original data map projections, where available. In the other cases it was used the UTM WGS84 Zone projected ccoordinate system where data fall in. Compared with the previous version this new version has been not only updated but was also reviewed (dataset schema and attributes values) in order to make it more compliant with INSPIRE.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8666c79c-fd1a-4d10-acc2-6040591c3117</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>ICES Statistical Areas</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Statistical units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fisheries management</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The ICES Statistical Areas delineates the divisions and subdivisions of FAO Major Fishing area 27.
The ICES Statistical Areas are used as bounding areas for calculation of fish statistics, e.g. catch per unit effort (CPUE) and stock estimates.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>40f1a7b4-eefd-41c2-bf53-a77bb136e02c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Regional Advisory Councils</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Maritime boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>This shape lists the areas covered by the Regional Advisory Councils (RAC) as poligons as exposed in the Atlas of the Seas. The Black Sea, Aquaculture, Markets and Outermost Regions Advisory Conucils have been added. Aditional information regarding to legal fundation have been added to the original shape.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>fe8e0abf-f7c0-44de-af6b-7493f2cbd4c7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>FAO Statistical Areas for Fishery Purposes</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Statistical units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fisheries management</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2014-04-17</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>FAO Major Fishing Areas for Statistical Purposes are arbitrary areas, the boundaries of which were determined in consultation with international fishery agencies on various considerations, including (i) the boundary of natural regions and the natural divisions of oceans and seas; (ii) the boundaries of adjacent statistical fisheries bodies already established in inter-governmental conventions and treaties; (iii) existing national practices; (iv) national boundaries; (v) the longitude and latitude grid system; (vi) the distribution of the aquatic fauna; and (vii) the distribution of the resources and the environmental conditions within an area. The rationale of the FAO Major Fishing Areas has been that the areas should, as far as possible, coincide with the areas of competence of other fishery commissions when existing. This system facilitates comparison of data, and improves the possibilities of cooperation in statistical matters in general.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4047aab8-be40-4c37-a981-b8e10710308a</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities, Cables, Actual Routes</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Utility and governmental services</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-05-11</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The datasets on submarine telecommunication cables (actual routes) were collected by Cogea starting from the 2014 for the European Marine Observation and Data Network. The underlying data are collated from a variety of sources: SIGCables (managed by Orange), the Federal Maritime and Hydrographic Agency (BSH Contis), Greg's Cable Map (via Kis-Orca), and the International Ocean Institute-Malta Operational Centre (University Of Malta/Physical Oceanography Unit, dataset originator: Transport Malta-Maritime Division, ex. Malta Maritime Authority). The datasets contain lines representing actual cable routes locations. Compared with the previous version, this version includes the location of submarine cables that originate from or pass through Maltese Waters.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>07987d84-6f1d-456a-adc8-a88165bbcbad</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Telecom cables</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Utility and governmental services</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2014-12-22</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset on submarine telecom cables was created by Cogea in 2014 for the European Marine Observation and Data Network. The underlying data are collated from a variety of sources: SIGCables (managed by Orange), the Federal Maritime and Hydrographic Agency (BSH Contis), and Greg's Cable Map (via Kis-Orca).The database contains lines representing actual cable routes locations.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8331978a-9414-410a-a9f4-94a7965c1dc0</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Dredging</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mineral resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>material</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>resource utilisation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>waste</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-06-15</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on dredging in the EU was created in 2014 by AZTI-Tecnalia for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains points representing dredging sites in the following countries: Belgium, Bulgaria, Cyprus, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania, Malta, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Spain, Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom. Where available, each point has the following attributes: Id (Identifier), Position Information (e.g.: Estimated, Original, Polygon centroid of dredging area, Polygon centroid of dredging polygon), Country, Sea basin, Extraction Area, Year, Permitted Amount (m3), Permitted Amount (t), Extracted Amount (m3), Extracted Amount (t), Extraction Type (e.g.: Harbour dredging, Estuary dredging, Sea lane), Purpose (e.g.: Maintenance dredging, Capital dredging, Others), End Use (e.g.: Beach nourishment, Commercialization, Confined deposit, Construction material, Embankment, Filling material, Land deposit, Reuse, Sea disposal, Wetland restoration), Material type (e.g.: silt, sand, gravel), Notes, Link to Web Sources.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>84af86e1-9d76-4739-b7f0-c9f2f3359419</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: International Convention marine area</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>International Convention Maritime Areas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>This dataset visualises the marine area with is covered by the Barcelona, Bucharest, HELCOM and OSPAR Convention.
Bucharest Convention dataset was locally created by cutting marine area of Black Sea and Sea of Azov.
HELCOM dataset was downloaded or connect via WMS to http://maps.helcom.fi/ArcGIS/services/DataDelivery/MapServer/WMSServer</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a4bfd2eb-bef8-423d-8ac1-48b7ded7058b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Emodnet_HA_Wind_farms_20180115</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Energy resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>energy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>wind farms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>economy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-15</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The database on offshore wind farms in the EU was created in 2014 by CETMAR for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is updated every year, and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains points and/or (where available) polygons  representing offshore wind farms in the following countries: Belgium, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Portugal, Spain, Sweden and United Kingdom. Each point has the following attributes (where available): Name, Nº of turbines, Status (Authorised, Operational, Planned, Under Construction), Country, Year, Website, Power (MW), Distance to coast (metres), Perimeter (kilometres), Surface (square kilometres) only for polygons. The distance to coast from polygon centroid or point has been calculated using the Reference Coordinates System with identifier EPSG: 3034 - Single CRS for all Europe (Used for conformal mapping at scales of 1:500,000 and smaller). Compared with the previous version this new version has been updated and reviewed.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c0c12986-4373-4cef-a1a4-75db11a4eafd</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Emodnet Human Activities - Major ports</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Transport networks</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>transportation</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-07-02</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on maritime transport in EU main ports includes goods, passengers and vessels traffic in the EU and was created in 2014 by Eurofish and Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided to EUROSTAT by ports in EU Member States and Norway. EUROSTAT data have been related to GISCO's georeferenced ports dataset. These datasets are updated on an annual basis. The latest update includes data up to 2017 (where available). Goods and Passengers data are available from 2001 while vessel is maintained from 2006 onwards. Goods traffic data are reported in thousand tonnes by type of cargo and direction. Passengers traffic data are reported in thousand passengers (excluding cruise passengers) by direction and traffic type. Vessels traffic data are reported in unit and gross tonnage (thousand) of vessels by vessel size class and vessel type. Original data is reported quarterly by EUROSTAT, but has been aggregated on an annual basis to produce this dataset.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a3743434-b9e3-4383-b19a-bb27277ab952</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Submerged Prehistoric Archeology</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Protected sites</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Protected Site</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>culture (society)</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset has been developped under the SPLASHCOS EU project, involving 20 EU Member States plus Norway, Russia, Ukraine and Switzerland. SPLASHCOS - Submerged Prehistoric Archaeology and Landscapes of the Continental Shelf - is a four-year research network (2009 to 2013) funded by the European Commission under its COST program (Cooperation in Science and Technology) as COST Action TD0902.
Its aim is to bring together archaeologists, marine geoscientists, heritage agencies, and commercial and industrial organizations interested in researching, managing and preserving the archives of archaeological and palaeoclimatic information locked up on the drowned prehistoric landscapes of the European continental shelf, and to disseminate that knowledge to a wider audience.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>633f2c70-f2e7-4527-b982-89c52bf2b0e9</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Emodnet Human Activities_MainPorts_Waste at ports</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Transport networks</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>waste</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>LEGISLATION, NORMS, CONVENTIONS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WASTES, POLLUTANTS, POLLUTION</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>transportation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on Main Ports - Waste at ports was created in 2018 by CETMAR using the Ports 2013 data available in Eurostat web page (http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/main/home). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). Following the MARPOL Convention waste at ports are quantified in metric tons (m3) and classified as oily waste (Annex I), garbage (Annex V), sewage (Annex IV), Harbor Waste (garbage) and Total Amount. These datasets are updated on an annual basis and includes annual data from 2004 to 2017 (where available) in the following countries:  Estonia, Finland, France, Latvia, Portugal and Spain.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c78e0e6c-8f3e-4d53-9c60-92105d297004</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Telecom cables (schematic routes)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Utility and governmental services</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-07-07</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset on submarine telecom cables was created by Cogea in 2014 for the European Marine Observation and Data Network. The underlying data is property of Telegeography and is available online at https://github.com/telegeography/www.submarinecablemap.com. Compared with the previous version, this version of includes the gigabit per second values that come from the Cable System Database of the Packet Clearing House organization and are available online at https://prefix.pch.net/applications/cablesystem/. The database contains lines and points representing cables and related landing points. Cables are represented as stylised paths, as actual cable routes locations are not available in most cases. The dataset includes any cable that crosses the EU waters (Marine regions). Marine regions and subregions boudaries are defined in Article 4 of the Marine Strategy Framework Directive (MSFD) and available online at https://www.eea.europa.eu/data-and-maps/data/msfd-regions-and-subregions.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b6f84844-726b-4fc6-a2a0-6b0686d5cc49</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities, Hydrocarbn Extraction: Offshore Installations</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Energy resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>energy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>hydrocarbon</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil exploration</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil extraction</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>offshore drilling</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oil production (chain)</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>petroleum industry</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-06-20</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on offshore installations in the EU was created in 2015 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is modelled on OSPAR's dataset on offshore installations, having the same fields and attributes.  OSPAR monitors the development of offshore installations and maintains an updated inventory of all oil and gas offshore installations in the OSPAR maritime area, the OSPAR Oil and Gas Offshore inventory. The database includes the name and ID number, location, operator, water depth, production start, current status, category and function of the installation. At present more than 1500 offshore installations are operational in the OSPAR maritime area, most of them sub-sea steel installations and fixed steel installations. Contracting Parties with oil and gas industry offshore installations are: Denmark, Germany, Ireland, the Netherlands, Norway, Spain and the United Kingdom.In addition, data on Italian offshore installations have been collected and harmonized from the Italian Ministry of Economic Development, from Marine Traffic and Helcom data on Polish and Russian installations in the Baltic Sea, from Marine Traffic data on Bulgarian, Russian and Ukrainian installations in the Black Sea, Lybian and Spanish installations in the Mediterranean Sea, from the Croatian Hydrocarbon Agency data on Croatian installations in the Adriatic Sea.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c0628d59-ecb6-4b03-9a16-970208f7d6f7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Lighhouses</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Buildings</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>built environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ANTHROPOSPHERE (built environment, human settlements, land setup)</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>RECREATION, TOURISM</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>TRAFFIC, TRANSPORTATION</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>building</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>tourism</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>transport</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Man-made object</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Traffic Flow Direction</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Waterway</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2015-08-13</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>This dataset provides the location of lighthouses inventoried by the Amateur Radio Lighthouse Society (ARLS). It includes both existing lighthouses and historical ones that have been removed, relocated or destroyed (column Status). The dataset includes the name of the lighthouse, its code in the ARLSH database and the gridsquare within which it is located. Coordinates are approximate for most of the lighthouses.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>5026492f-5e70-4975-ba86-40e2d21ebc99</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Finfish farming sites</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Agricultural and aquaculture facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>AGRICULTURE, FORESTRY; ANIMAL HUSBANDRY; FISHERY</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fish farming</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-07-06</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset provides information about the location of seawater finfish farms in the EU and partner countries where data are available. There is an obligation for MS to inventory all authorized aquaculture sites under the Council Directive 2006/88/EC on animal health requirements. Despite this obligation, the availability of data varies significantly among MS from no data available at all to a complete regularly updated dataset (e.g.in Scotland). Most MS with only a marginal finfish production are not able to provide a list with the geolacation of farms. In the main producer countries, there is usually a public list of authorized farms with geolocation data and sometimes information on the species. Data is provided here for Cyprus, Denmark, Greece, Ireland, Finland, Norway, Spain and the UK. There are no sea-based finfish farms in Belgium, Bulgaria, Latvia, Lithuania, the Netherlands and Poland. Data are still missing in other EU MS. In the last version from June 28 2017, data for Norway was added and the layer was updated with new attributes. Main species have been listed as Yes/No/n.a. attributes (Arctic Char, Cod, Halibut, Lumpfish, Meagre, Salmon, Seabass, Seabream, Trout, Tuna, Turbot, Wolffish, Wrasse and Other Species) and the detailed original description of species has been added in a separate attribute. Information on Production Stage (Grow out for Human consumption, Hatchery, Nursery, Reproduction, Brood stock, Other) has been added for Greece, Norway and partially for Spain. Information on purpose (Commercial, Research, Education, Display) has been added for Norway.   Status (Active, Application, Expired, Expired in Use, Inactive, Notice, Revised, Renewal) is provided for Ireland, Norway (only active farms) and the UK. Point information indicates if the data points correspond to the data provided by the Source ("Original") or if they have been estimated by the Emodnet team when Polygons were provided ("Polygon centroid", in Ireland only).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>590a0091-5a7e-454d-9d3b-737bb7ccbc38</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Offshore Pipelines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Utility and governmental services</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Pipe</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Transport Network</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Transport Object</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>EFFECTS, IMPACTS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>TRAFFIC, TRANSPORTATION</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>energy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Pipelines</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-12-20</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on offshore pipelines in the EU was created in 2017 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all over the EU (plus Norway). The database contains lines representing the actual routes of offshore pipelines (where available) in the following countries: Croatia, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, Germany, Ireland, Netherlands, Norway, Poland, Russia, Spain (Andalucía). Each line has the following harmonized attributes (where available): status (in service, decommissioned, under construction, proposed, planned), country, code, name, year, medium (air, condensate, 'control', cooling water, gas, geothermal heating, glycol, methanol, oil, sewage, water), operator, from and to locality or facility, length (metres) and size (inches).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>eb3625c1-48eb-4ca7-8c3d-ed5a5579da55</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Aggregate Extraction</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mineral resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-06-20</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on aggregate extractions in the EU was created in 2014 by AZTI-Tecnalia for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains points representing aggregate extraction sites, by year (although some data are indicated by a period of years), in the following countries: Belgium, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Ireland, Italy, Poland, Spain, Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom.  Where available, each point has the following attributes: Id (Identifier), Position Info (e.g.: Estimated, Original, Polygon centroid of dredging area, Estimated polygon centroid of dredging area), Country, Sea basin, Name of the extraction area, Area of activity (km2), Year (the year when the extraction took place), Permitted Amount (m3) (permitted amount of material to be extracted, in m3), Permitted Amount (t) (permitted amount of material to be extracted, in tonnes), Requested Amount (m3) (requested amount of material to be extracted, in m3), Requested Amount (t) (requested amount of material to be extracted, in tonnes), Extracted Amount (m3) (extracted amount of material, in m3), Extracted Amount (t) (extracted amount of material, in tonnes), Extraction Type (Marine sediment extraction), Purpose (e.g.: Commercial, Others, N/A), End Use (e.g.: Beach nourishment, Construction, Reclamation fill, N/A), Material type (e.g.: sand, gravel, maerl), Notes, Link to Web Sources.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>ccc4cd96-a838-4368-8a7f-9e2637a8b3ef</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Vessel Density 2017</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>TIFF</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2019-03-11</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>EMODnet Vessel Density Map were created by Cogea in 2019 in the framework of EMODnet Human Activities, an initiative funded by the EU Commission. The maps are based on AIS data purchased by CLS and show shipping density in 1km*1km cells of a grid covering all EU waters (and some neighbouring areas). Density is expressed as hours per square kilometre per month. The following ship types are available:0 Other, 1 Fishing, 2 Service, 3 Dredging or underwater ops, 4 Sailing, 5 Pleasure Craft, 6 High speed craft, 7 Tug and towing, 8 Passenger, 9 Cargo, 10T anker, 11 Military and Law Enforcement, 12 Unknown and All ship types. Data are available by month of year. Yearly averages are also available.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>41abc48f-d231-48ad-9b20-e769ec767f16</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Aggregate (Areas)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mineral resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-09-19</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on areas for aggregate extractions in the EU was created in 2018 by AZTI-Tecnalia for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains polygons representing areas of seabed licensed for exploration or extraction of aggregates, in the following countries: Belgium, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Italy, Lithuania, Poland, Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom.  Where available, each polygon has the following attributes: Id (Identifier), Area code, Area name, Country, Sea basin, Starting year (the year when the license starts), End year (the year when the license ends), Site Type (exploration or extraction area), License status (Active, not active, unknown), Material type (e.g.: sand, gravel, maerl), Notes, Distance to coast (in metres), Link to Web Sources.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>Emodnet_HA_Aggregates_20180920</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Aggregate Extraction</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mineral resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-09-20</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on aggregate extractions in the EU was created in 2014 by AZTI-Tecnalia for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains points representing aggregate extraction sites and activities by year (although some data are indicated by a period of years), in the following countries: Belgium, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Ireland, Italy, Poland, Spain, Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom.  Where available, each point has the following attributes: Id (Identifier), Position Info (e.g.: Estimated, Original, Polygon centroid of dredging area, Estimated polygon centroid of dredging area), Country, Sea basin, Name of the extraction area, Area of activity (km2), Year (the year when the extraction took place), Permitted Amount (m3) (permitted amount of material to be extracted, in m3), Permitted Amount (t) (permitted amount of material to be extracted, in tonnes), Requested Amount (m3) (requested amount of material to be extracted, in m3), Requested Amount (t) (requested amount of material to be extracted, in tonnes), Extracted Amount (m3) (extracted amount of material, in m3), Extracted Amount (t) (extracted amount of material, in tonnes), Extraction Type (Marine sediment extraction), Purpose (e.g.: Commercial, Others, N/A), End Use (e.g.: Beach nourishment, Construction, Reclamation fill, N/A), Material type (e.g.: sand, gravel, maerl), Notes, Link to Web Sources.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>cd14c965-72ee-434e-9a2a-956758639507</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities, Algae Production</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Algae farming</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Agricultural and aquaculture facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>farming</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>economy</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>structure</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-10-09</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>This dataset stems from the BIOMASS project (https://ec.europa.eu/knowledge4policy/projects-activities/jrc-biomass-assessment-study_en). Its aim is to build a reliable database to characterize the algae sector and to support informed European policies on Blue Growth and Bioeconomy. In the framework of this project, a joint workshop between JRC, FAO and the COST Actions Phycomorph and EUalgae was organized, where the knowledge gaps and needs regarding algae biomass production were discussed. As a first step in this project information on the location of the production facilities, group of produced organism (macro/microalgae) and production method (Fermenters, Photobioreactors, Open ponds, Semi Open ponds, Photobioreactors and open ponds, Photobioreactors and fermenters, Pilot, Harvesting; land-based, off-shore and coastal Aquaculture, Integrated multi-trophic or not) have been collected in the following countries: Austria, Belgium, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Faroe Islands, France, Germany, Iceland, Ireland, Italy, Netherlands, Norway, Portugal, Spain, Sweden, and UK. The list of European algae producers is based on the list provided by European Algae Biomass Association (EABA) and combined with JRC list</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a93bbd2a-0f03-4d60-9d3a-112a7ccd6a02</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Emodnet_HA_OMA_EEZ</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Area management/restriction/regulation zones and reporting units</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Maritime boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Resource management</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2018-05-09</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Economic Exclusive Zones boundaries include polygons for 200 nautical miles. The EEZs included in the dataset are those for which a regulatory text exists in the framework of UNCLOS, following the web page of the Division for Ocean Affairs and the Law of the Sea, Office of Legal Affairs, United Nations (http://www.un.org/depts/los/LEGISLATIONANDTREATIES/toc.htm). Each polygon has the following attributes: Country, Territory (in case of overseas territories), legal document name that establishes the EEZ for each country (Act, Royal Decree or Law, Proclamation or Executive Order), date of established EEZ, Law of the Sea Zone Type Identifier, Law of the Sea Nature of the Delimitation Name (it provides the number of states involved within the juridical text signed) and Nomenclature of Territorial Units for Statistics (NUTS) standard for EU.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>emodnet_submarine_ volcanoes_polygons_250k</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Submarine Volcanoes Polygons (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>submarine volcano, marine geology, geological event</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine volcanoes, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Locally occurrences include their emerged portions. Note: Project is ongoing and the work is in progress; blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>emodnet_submarine_ volcanoes_lines_250k</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Submarine Volcanoes Lines (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>submarine volcano, marine geology, geological event</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine volcanoes, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Lines refer to eruptive fissures or borders of lava flows. Note: Project is ongoing and the work is in progress; blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>5BED5077-56A2-433D-8DA3-382B278685A9</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Submarine Landslides Lines (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>submarine landslide, marine geology, geological event</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine landslides scarps, detectable on the seabed, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4C861DDC-E101-47D8-AE87-84CDAA6B9D4D</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Submarine Fluid Emissions Polygons (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>fluid emission, vent, seep, marine geology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine mud-volcanoes and fluid emissions of non volcanic origin, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>7B724C1B-B847-47EE-A865-2D0B419B2B41</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>emodnet_submarine_landslides_polygons_250k</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>submarine landslide, marine geology, geological event</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine landslides, detectable on the seabed, outcropping or buried, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Locally landslides are extended on land to include their origin.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>53A9BFE4-BCB1-424F-B6E8-02A89890E679</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Submarine Fluid Emissions Points (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>fluid emission, vent, seep, marine geology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine mud-volcanoes and fluid emissions of non volcanic origin, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Points refer to areas smaller than 60 hectares.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>emodnet_tsunamis_origin_points_250k</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Tsunamis Origin Points (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>tsunami, submarine earthquake, marine geology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Locations of events which originated tsunamis, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Where possible, connected events reported in other EMODnet Geology layers are indicated. Note: Project is ongoing and the work is in progress; blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>emodnet_submarine_ volcanoes_points_250k</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Submarine Volcanoes Points (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>submarine volcano, marine geology, geological event</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine volcanoes, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Points refer to specific morphotypes or areas smaller than 60 hectares. Note: Project is ongoing and the work is in progress; blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>3ddf80ea-d8d0-4aaa-b8eb-d25a6ed8c468</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Wrecks</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Protected sites</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Protected Site</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>culture (society)</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset has been developped under the MACHU EU project, involving seven EU MS (BE, DE, NL, PL, PT, UK, SE). The MACHU GIS database provides information about wrecks, sites and objects underwater. MACHU is an applications on Underwater Cultural Heritage providing historic and archaeological information. MACHU is not intended to give exact positions of wrecks an site, in the aim of ensuring their protection.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>BEC0C3B7-D49C-4424-9F1A-D4FE94119AFE</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet_WP6_Quaternary_tectonics_lin_250k</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>submarine tectonics, fault, marine geology, structural geology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Quaternary submarine tectonic lines in geologically active areas, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d32d7b01-4d38-4e44-9206-42d5a5fe705b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Freshwater farming sites</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Agricultural and aquaculture facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>AGRICULTURE, FORESTRY; ANIMAL HUSBANDRY; FISHERY</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fishery</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>fish farming</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-10-09</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The dataset provides information about the location of freshwater finfish farms in the EU and partner countries where data are available. There is an obligation for EU MS to inventory all authorized aquaculture sites under the Council Directive 2006/88/EC on animal health requirements. Despite this obligation, the availability of data varies among MS from no data available at all to a complete regularly updated dataset (e.g.in Scotland). As far as partner countries are concerned, data have been collected in Norway only at this stage, where detailed data are provided online. Data provided here cover Austria, Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Denmark, Greece, Ireland, Norway, Poland, Slovenia, Spain, and the UK. Data collection is still undergoing in other EU MS and neighbouring countries. In some countries, the list of authorized establishments clearly indicates the status (e.g. in Ireland: active, inactive, expired, etc..) or provides relevant information (e.g. in the UK- Scotland: production in the last 3 years : Y/N), but in most MS the status is only partially fulfilled or not provided. In Norway, only active farms have been included at this stage. Available information on species has been harmonised. Filters are available for the following main species: Carp, Catfish, “Other freshwater pond fish” (zander, pike, perch, tench, etc. – mostly cyprinidae), Trout, Salmon (smolt and juveniles), Eel,  Sturgeon, Tilapia, Ornamental Fish and Other. There is no information on species in Austria, Czech Republic and Slovenia (information is available in Czech Republic but not in a usable format at this stage). The field Detailed species provides an English translation of the species descriptions from the sources (before harmonisation). Information on Production Stage (Grow out, Hatchery, Nursery, Brood stock, Research, Other) and Farm type (Closed systems, Ponds, Tanks-Raceways, Quarantine facility, Research facility, Other) is at least partially available for most countries. Point information indicates if the data points correspond to the data provided by the Source ("Original") or if they have been estimated by the Emodnet team when Polygons were provided ("Polygon centroid"). Polygons were provided in Ireland only.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>30ff73ab-3352-4082-919d-2197bf78d791</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Status of Bathing Waters</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Environmental monitoring facilities</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>bathing water</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>bathing seawater</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>water analysis</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>water monitoring</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>water pollution</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>water protection area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>water quality management</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>recreational area</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>mass recreation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2016-06-13</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on status of coastal and transitonal bathing water categories in the EU was created in 2015 by Cogea for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is based on the dataset "Bathing Water Directive - Status of bathing water" provided by The European Topic Centre on Water and made available by the European Environment Agency at https://www.eea.europa.eu/data-and-maps/data/bathing-water-directive-status-of-bathing-water-9. The data set presents the latest information as reported by the Member States (EU28) for the 2016 bathing season, as well as some historical data since 1990, and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The geographic coverage is: Albania, Belgium, Bulgaria, Croatia, Cyprus, Denmark, Estonia, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Latvia, Lithuania, Malta, Netherlands, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Slovenia, Spain, Sweden, United Kingdom.The whole EEA datatset is also available for download purpose (xlsx file). It includes data on the other two categories of water sampled (river, lake) toghether with data on bathing waters status in Austria, Czech Republic, Luxembourg, Slovakia, and Switzerland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>7553249d-43dd-489a-acd4-3eeb7ffdbfc5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Human Activities: Ocean Energy Test Sites</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Energy resources</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>utilitiesCommunication</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>unknown</dc:format>
      <dct:modified>2017-06-19</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>The geodatabase on Ocean Energy test sites in the EU was created in 2016 by AZTI-Tecnalia for the European Marine Observation and Data Network (EMODnet). It is the result of the aggregation and harmonization of datasets provided by several sources from all across the EU. It is updated every year, and is available for viewing and download on EMODnet - Human Activities web portal (www.emodnet-humanactivities.eu). The database contains polygons representing Ocean Energy test sites in the following countries: Denmark, France, Ireland, Norway, Portugal, Spain, Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom. Where available, each polygon has the following attributes: test site code, name, location, country, sea basin, distance to coast (metres), resource type (wave, tidal), starting year, ending year, lease status, site status, capacity (kW), depth (metres), area (square km), grid connection, number of berths, developer, position info (it indicates if the attribute value is original from the source or has been estimated).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8ac7f893-a722-4a9b-b7b2-a82451228bab</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_PSMSL_SLEV_Anomalies - Sea Level Anomalies - PSMSL</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Relative Sea Level Anomalies</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Observed Sea Level</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Global mean sea level trends since 1900. EMODnet Physics - PSMSL, Data Retrived 30/04/2018 from http://www.psmsl.org/data/obtaining; (http://www.psmsl.org/data/obtaining/reference.php)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>da38f3f2-0674-4b40-8fc1-c7214c5880df</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_ARC_TEMP_Climatology.1.1 - Arctic Temperature Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Arctic Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Temperature Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a908feeb-4871-4d90-a533-7bd7bf09c01c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_CMEMS_PSAL_CORA_5.1 - CORA Global Ocean Water Column Salinity Monthly Gridded reanalisys v.5.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Monthly gridded analysis fields of Salinity profiles from the reprocessed (ISAS software) in-situ  data collections (1900 - 201x). INSITU_GLO_TS_OA_REP_OBSERVATIONS_013_002_b - Developed by IFREMER for CMEMS - re-distributed by EMODnet Physics</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>2f49f009-2b5d-45cb-a8e6-4738461ec8ad</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_MED_PSAL_Climatology.1.1 - Mediterranean Sea Salinity Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Salinity Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d709283e-3406-4bca-a5f5-1ba7f05ec37e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_BLS_TEMP_Climatology.1.1 - Black Sea Temperature Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Black Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Sea of Azov</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Temperature Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>1b750664-7007-497f-b34c-0f0ba946d990</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_TSM - Monthly time series of Total Suspended Matter (TSM)</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Total Suspended Matter</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>European Seas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Total Suspended Matter</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Concentration of total suspended matter (conc_tsm, mg/l) is a product of the Coastcolour L2W Concentrations Data, obtained from the OC4 algorithm for clear and moderate turbid waters, and from the CoastColour v1 neural network.The L2W product was then remapped on a regular grid, maintaining the 300 m full resolution, in order to obtain L3 products over the European Seas and monthly averaged. Developed by EMODnet Physics.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>91dcab9f-a6f6-46fe-95bc-eff22c391a36</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_HFR_NRT_SSC - Sea Surface Currents</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Sea Surface Currents</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>West-East Current Component</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>South-North Current Component</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>In situ gridded Sea Surface Currents as monitored by High Frequency Radars</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>7d112207-260f-49a9-9ba7-2ed0c67bbd58</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_PSMSL_SLEV_REL - Relative Sea Level Trends</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Relative Sea Level trends</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Observed Sea Level</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Global mean sea level trends since 1900.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>1699ca18-c328-4c8c-b9c4-ee6826cbba43</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SONEL_SLEV_ABS - Absolute Sea Level Trends</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Absolute Sea Level trends</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Observed Sea Level</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Global mean sea level trends since 1900. Developed by SONEL - re-distributed by EMODnet Physics</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>3643734c-9bcb-4429-a2f9-27520e0b01ab</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_NWS_TEMP_Climatology.1.1 - North Sea Temperature Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North West Shelf - North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Temperature Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>90ae7a06-8b08-4afe-83dd-ca92bc99f5c0</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_MED_TEMP_Climatology.1.1 - Mediterranean Sea Temperature Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Temperature Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d7ea15be-084d-4d32-bd59-92d623703cae</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_CMEMS_TEMP_CORA_5.1 - CORA Global Ocean Water Column Temperature Monthly Gridded reanalisys v.5.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Monthly gridded analysis fields of Temperature profiles from the reprocessed (ISAS software) in-situ  data collections (1900 - 201x). INSITU_GLO_TS_OA_REP_OBSERVATIONS_013_002_b - Developed by IFREMER for CMEMS - re-distributed by EMODnet Physics</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>18be95d5-fbbb-4a61-afeb-eb5e182a1a3d</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_MEOP_PSAL_2017 - Marine Mammals Exploring the Oceans Pole to Pole - MEOP - Salinity in the water column</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Since 2004, several hundred thousands profiles of temperature and salinity have been collected by instrumented animals. The use of elephant seals has been particularly effective to sample the Southern Ocean and the North Pacific. These hydrographic data have been assembled in a quality-controlled database, the MEOP-CTD database.
The marine mammal data were collected and made freely available by the International MEOP Consortium and the national programs that contribute to it. (http://www.meop.net). - Distributed by EMODnet Physics.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>cdc02af0-bab2-4b0e-8758-0091ffcc5e11</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_IBI_TEMP_Climatology.1.1 - Atlantic Iberian Biscay Irish Sea Temperature Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Atlantic Iberian Biscay Irish Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Temperature Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a5bd2eb2-0f81-47f4-b091-b04214529b52</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_INSITU_NRT_7 - NRT IN SITU LATEST 7 DAYS Collection</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature and salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North West Shelf - North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Atmospheric data at sea level</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Sea ice coverage</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Sea level trends</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Light attenuation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Horizontal velocity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Sea surface currents</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Wave height and period</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Wind speed and direction,</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Global oceans collection of the in situ operational (Near Real Time) and historical validated data on water column temperature, water column salinity, currents, waves, winds at sea level, sea level, ligh attenuation, biogeochemical data, river runoff, under water noise. It is based on CMEMS INSITU NRT products, integrated with non European data sources.
Distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>9f4751af-a499-41a2-8286-9f761c0549f9</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_NWS_PSAL_Climatology.1.1 - North Sea Salinity Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North West Shelf - North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Salinity Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>017d62cf-750f-494d-a103-6239fdafd0c7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_BAL_PSAL_Climatology.1.1 - Baltic Sea Salinity Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Baltic Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Salinity Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b12895e8-a4f6-40fa-8ed9-96153c7572da</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_CMEMS_SIC_ANTARCTIC - Sea Ice coverage - Antarctic Oceans</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Sea Ice Coverage</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Antarctic Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>For the Global - Arctic and Antarctic - Ocean. The OSI SAF delivers three global sea ice products in operational mode: sea ice concentration, sea ice edge, sea ice type (OSI-401 OSI-402 and OSI-403). These products are delivered daily at 10km resolution in a polar stereographic projection covering the Northern Hemisphere and the Southern Hemisphere. It is the Sea Ice operational nominal product for the Global Ocean. In addition, a sea ice drift product is delivered at 60km resolution in a polar stereographic projection covering the Northern and Southern Hemispheres. The sea ice motion vectors have a time-span of 2 days.
SEAICE_GLO_SEAICE_L4_NRT_OBSERVATIONS_011_001 - Developed by SIW-METNO-OSLO-NO for CMEMS - re-distributed by EMODnet Physics.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c24e66ae-7c2c-420a-ad9b-9b02652759ea</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_CMEMS_SIC_ARCTIC - Sea Ice coverage - Arctic Oceans</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Sea Ice Coverage</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Arctic Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>For the Global - Arctic and Antarctic - Ocean. The OSI SAF delivers three global sea ice products in operational mode: sea ice concentration, sea ice edge, sea ice type (OSI-401 OSI-402 and OSI-403). These products are delivered daily at 10km resolution in a polar stereographic projection covering the Northern Hemisphere and the Southern Hemisphere. It is the Sea Ice operational nominal product for the Global Ocean. In addition, a sea ice drift product is delivered at 60km resolution in a polar stereographic projection covering the Northern and Southern Hemispheres. The sea ice motion vectors have a time-span of 2 days.
SEAICE_GLO_SEAICE_L4_NRT_OBSERVATIONS_011_001 - Developed by SIW-METNO-OSLO-NO for CMEMS - re-distributed by EMODnet Physics</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d3d20baf-a27d-4ad3-abcc-e4c67ff17c9d</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_UWN_INR - European Impulsive Noise events Registry</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Impulsive under water noise events</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>European Seas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2017-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Data supplied by contracting parties to OSPAR (North East Atlantic), HELCOM (Baltic Sea), and Barcelona and ACCOBAMS (Mediterranean Sea, Black Sea). The data are collated nationally from registers of licenced events such as pile driving, controlled explosions from naval operations and other activities that release energy. This registry is specifically purposed with supporting OSPAR and HELCOM in providing information that will feed their regional assessments, and in reporting by its contracting parties to MSFD descriptor 11.1.1 (Low and mid frequency impulsive noise).
HELCOM and OSPAR impulsive noise events registry is hosted and managed by ICES (http://ices.dk/marine-data/data-portals/Pages/underwater-noise.aspx), ACCOBAMS impulsive noise event registry is hosted @ http://accobams.noiseregister.org. EMODnet Physics is integrating and distributing the different sources (www.emodnet-physcs.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a121723f-3686-48d9-8cd5-9a6ff92adf64</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_ARC_PSAL_Climatology.1.1 - Arctic Salinity Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Arctic Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Salinity Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>0cdd65a5-29b5-4591-bc23-3556eadbea0b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_MEOP_TEMP_2017 - Marine Mammals Exploring the Oceans Pole to Pole - MEOP - Temperature in the water column</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Global Oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Since 2004, several hundred thousands profiles of temperature and salinity have been collected by instrumented animals. The use of elephant seals has been particularly effective to sample the Southern Ocean and the North Pacific. These hydrographic data have been assembled in a quality-controlled database, the MEOP-CTD database. 
The marine mammal data were collected and made freely available by the International MEOP Consortium and the national programs that contribute to it. (http://www.meop.net). - Distributed by EMODnet Physics</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c53c5f33-7037-40d3-af56-573a59c24f01</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_IBI_PSAL_Climatology.1.1 - Atlantic Iberian Biscay Irish Sea Salinity Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Atlantic Iberian Biscay Irish Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Salinity Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d47e419d-fbba-4120-934b-84c8a07cf6b7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_BAL_TEMP_Climatology.1.1 - Baltic Sea Temperature Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Baltic Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Temperature of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Temperature Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>482a26d1-3547-449d-9e25-7bb1c53d524a</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EP_SDN_BLS_PSAL_Climatology.1.1 - Black Sea Salinity Climatology V1.1</dc:title>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Oceanographic geographical features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Black Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Sea of Azov</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Salinity of the water column</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>climatologyMeteorologyAtmosphere</dc:subject>
      <dct:modified>2018-01-01</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Salinity Climatology  (1900-2013) - based on the SeaDataNet aggregated dataset - DIVA software v4.6.10 - mask: relative error threshold 0.5. Developed by SeaDataNet (https://www.seadatanet.org), distributed by EMODnet Physics (www.emodnet-physics.eu)</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>7a15cab24d258a9006d7685fcea85fe215a68266</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Gridded abundances of marine species (3 year average)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Species_gridded_abundances_3year</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>This dataproduct consists of a set of gridded map layers showing the average abundance of different species of species groups for different time windows (seasonal, annual or multi-annual as appropriate) using spatial modelling.
They cover a wide taxonomic range, from the smallest organisms (e.g. diatoms, flagellates) to the largest ones (e.g. fish, birds, reptiles, mammals), encompassing all trophic levels.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>701d7e745a6d309ae68cfd72d400a57a09c3625c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>OOPS products</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>OOPS_products</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Copepods</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Abundance</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Spatial modelling</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North Atlantic Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Shapefile containing a set of gridded map layers showing the average abundance of the six most abundant Copepod species  from the CPR for different time windows (seasonal, annual) using geospatial modelling. The spatial modelling tool used to calculate the gridded abundance maps is based on DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c0f1328f85ba9a424dfccbddec64e74f45d0d3d5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>OOPS errors</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>OOPS_errors</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Error values</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Spatial modelling</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Abundance</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Copepods</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North Atlanitc Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Shapefile containing the error values of the spatial modelling tool DIVA  used to calculate the gridded abundance maps of the six most abundant Copepod species  from the CPR for different time windows (seasonal, annual) using geospatial modelling.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>2dd12af42b11513c11d80c19764d1bb4f4855edc</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>OOPS regions</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>OOPS_regions</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Marine regions</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Atlantic Ocean</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Boundaries</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Shapefile containing ICES ecoregions and Western Atlantic Hydrographic regions for the development of ICES operational Oceanographic Products and Services.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>700ab841af219a3efb3d2bcdf60a7176952ee4ae</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Gridded abundances of marine species (2 year average)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Species_gridded_abundances_2year</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract />
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f6fb38044c1d25866aa649f37d9a192645460cd0</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Species gridded abundance all</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Species_gridded_abundance_all</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract />
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>089f454546dc01fc72121b1fca67a823d865b1b3</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>OOPS products (VLIZ)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>OOPS_products_vliz</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract />
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>30355457f917d53c0295ecd80dba5ab751e20d81</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Absences of coralligenous outcrop (polygons)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Corals</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Absence data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coral absence (polygons) form the Mediterranean Sea. Data from  Coralligenous and mäerl beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). A lot for information has been derived from three critical sources: the first is the Action plan for the conservation of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean Sea by the UNEP-MAP-RAC/SPA (2008) followed by the report in the State of knowledge of the geographical distribution of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean by UNEP (2009).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4026d70d1a4e9e83dd0939b9cf398e6140e453e7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Occurrences of coralligenous outcrop (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Corals</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>point distributions</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coral point distributions form dataset  Coralligenous and mäerl beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). A lot for information has been derived from three critical sources: the first is the Action plan for the conservation of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean Sea by the UNEP-MAP-RAC/SPA (2008) followed by the report in the State of knowledge of the geographical distribution of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean by UNEP (2009).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>bb7a0725b0ae1094208750b1f3abb1067ce87a96</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Occurrences of coralligenous outcrop (polygons)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Corals</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coral polygon data Mediterranean Sea from dataset Coralligenous and mäerl beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). A lot for information has been derived from three critical sources: the first is the Action plan for the conservation of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean Sea by the UNEP-MAP-RAC/SPA (2008) followed by the report in the State of knowledge of the geographical distribution of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean by UNEP (2009).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c54bed4920864e7c819ac8142c6fc30534c4f494</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Absences of coralligenous outcrop (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Corals</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Absence data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coral Absence Data from the dataset Coralligenous and mäerl beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). A lot for information has been derived from three critical sources: the first is the Action plan for the conservation of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean Sea by the UNEP-MAP-RAC/SPA (2008) followed by the report in the State of knowledge of the geographical distribution of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean by UNEP (2009).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>0c550b918e2b9b647580618bbc99a7bf64fc688d</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Calanus helgolandicus masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>cal_hel_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Calanus helgolandicus. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8148dd43eec996b8c3bd99083f59d9a81173c035</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Calanus finmarchicus masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>cal_fin_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Calanus finmarchicus. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8f680ce5ced0050d51d7afd6a44c94c8439cd42c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance chlorophyll index masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>chli_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded map of the abundance of the chlorophyll index. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8f27d41239d55feb6d920b48378d1ae89857cef2</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Acartia spp. masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>aca_spp_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Acartia spp. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>32f28bf7144b27fd2a1568131944be578938a043</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Acartia spp. masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>aca_spp_19582016_L1</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Acartia spp. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>e40837e97a44b9c33d49b0fdd10a9ee4bb1ef3a2</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Modelled Spatial Distributions of Coralligenous Habitats (2014)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Coralligenous formations</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Coralligenous formations</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coralligenous formations and mäerl beds are typical benthic seascape features of the Mediterranean Sea, and are protected habitats under Council Regulation (EC) No 1967/2006. Despite their ecological importance in terms of biodiversity and ecosystem services, knowledge on the spatial distribution of these two “habitats” remains scattered. In Task 1.3 of the “Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats” project (MEDISEH), the objective was to develop species distribution models for coralligenous formations and mäerl beds, so as to predict their occurrence at poorly-sampled and un-sampled areas. Using models in predictive mode, continuous habitat maps were created for the Mediterranean basin: these maps help identify areas where these habitats are likely to be found, and where they are likely to be absent. Please refer to the final report of the MEDISEH project (section on Task 1.3) for full details on the methodology, results and interpretation of the maps showing the predicted occurrence probability for coralligenous formations (Figures 1.3.15a-d, “Coralligenous.jpg”) and mäerl beds (Figure 1.3.18a-d, “Maerl.jpg”). The spatial datasets underlying the maps are given here in several formats (raster, Google Earth, shapefile), all using the WGS 1984 datum (as coordinate system). The ESRI grid raster (floating point) has a spatial resolution of 0.004166 decimal degrees, and the values 0 and 1 correspond to the lowest and highest occurrence probabilities, respectively. The raster is also available as Google Earth compatible file (.kml format). The ESRI polygon shapefile presents the same information as the raster, but continuous values were classed in bins ranging from 0 to 10 (i.e. from lowest to highest occurrence probability). The work was financed through a service contract for the Directorate-General for Maritime Affairs and Fisheries (DG-MARE), 2011-2013. Please contact Dr. Corinne Martin (main author, corinne.sophie.martin@gmail.com), or Dr. Marianna Giannoulaki (MEDISEH Project Coordinator, Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, marianna@hcmr.gr) for use restrictions, and citation.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a92261b019fda26943128cd911570911db38de4e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Modelled Spatial Distributions of Maërl Habitats (2014)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mäerl beds</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Mäerl beds are typical benthic seascape features of the Mediterranean Sea, and are protected habitats under Council Regulation (EC) No 1967/2006. Despite their ecological importance in terms of biodiversity and ecosystem services, knowledge on the spatial distribution of these two “habitats” remains scattered. In Task 1.3 of the “Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats” project (MEDISEH), the objective was to develop species distribution models for coralligenous formations and mäerl beds, so as to predict their occurrence at poorly-sampled and un-sampled areas. Using models in predictive mode, continuous habitat maps were created for the Mediterranean basin: these maps help identify areas where these habitats are likely to be found, and where they are likely to be absent. Please refer to the final report of the MEDISEH project (section on Task 1.3) for full details on the methodology, results and interpretation of the maps showing the predicted occurrence probability for coralligenous formations (Figures 1.3.15a-d, “Coralligenous.jpg”) and mäerl beds (Figure 1.3.18a-d, “Maerl.jpg”). The spatial datasets underlying the maps are given here in several formats (raster, Google Earth, shapefile), all using the WGS 1984 datum (as coordinate system). The ESRI grid raster (floating point) has a spatial resolution of 0.004166 decimal degrees, and the values 0 and 1 correspond to the lowest and highest occurrence probabilities, respectively. The raster is also available as Google Earth compatible file (.kml format). The ESRI polygon shapefile presents the same information as the raster, but continuous values were classed in bins ranging from 0 to 10 (i.e. from lowest to highest occurrence probability). The work was financed through a service contract for the Directorate-General for Maritime Affairs and Fisheries (DG-MARE), 2011-2013. Please contact Dr. Corinne Martin (main author, corinne.sophie.martin@gmail.com), or Dr. Marianna Giannoulaki (MEDISEH Project Coordinator, Hellenic Centre for Marine Research, marianna@hcmr.gr) for use restrictions, and citation.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>248bb4c784b2918e22354e7dc88142211c939bf5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Maërl bed occurences (points) in the Mediterranean Sea</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Maerl beds</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>point distributions</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Point data of occurrences of Maerl beds from dataset Coralligenous and mäerl beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). A lot for information has been derived from three critical sources: the first is the Action plan for the conservation of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean Sea by the UNEP-MAP-RAC/SPA (2008) followed by the report in the State of knowledge of the geographical distribution of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean by UNEP (2009).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a519ede941324c8bacbb23f8fbd60f03e3a1e2b4</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Maërl bed occurences (polygons) in the Mediterranean Sea</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Maerl beds</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Maerl bed polygon data Mediterranean Sea from dataset Coralligenous and mäerl beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). A lot for information has been derived from three critical sources: the first is the Action plan for the conservation of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean Sea by the UNEP-MAP-RAC/SPA (2008) followed by the report in the State of knowledge of the geographical distribution of the coralligenous and other calcareous bio-concretions in the Mediterranean by UNEP (2009).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>082eee17385be154aeaa332b83c6e84d9d08ea27</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution - Coastline of Known Absence (line)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Absence data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastline with real absence of Posidonia oceanica meadows from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>130a074c7c4d740e34b78d7b117fa8770846eb8f</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution - Current Distribution (polygons)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Current Posidonia oceanica distribution in the Mediterranean Sea from dataset from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a7454358bf4d6ece56ba3d42573792e45d60fb61</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution - Current Distribution (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Current Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution (presence
points) in the Mediterranean Sea from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a9a0d0a641aa78da0ab3c5863a157e1e18d9eca0</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Halophila stipulacea beds distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Halophila stipulacea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Halophila stipulacea beds distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean
Sea from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH).The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4b0796b0a41090a001978753a177ab6aaa6738d3</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Cymodocea nodosa beds distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Cymodocea nodosa</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Cymodocea nodosa beds distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean
Sea. Contact person is MAREA Consortium, andrea.belluscio@uniroma1.it</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>3a671e073977696262d63b0e93cb0bdb193ce311</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Modelled Posidonia oceanica Distribution (2013)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Biogenic habitat</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranea Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>This dataset shows the modelled spatial distribution of Posidonia oceanica seagrass in the Mediterranean Sea. Posidonia oceanica is endemic to the Mediterranean Sea, where it is the dominant seagrass. It is found in sandy and rocky areas down to depths of about 45 m. P. oceanica is a protected species under European and international law, as well as several national legislations. 

 	

The model was built based on an (observed) P. oceanica occurrence dataset extracted from a Mediterranean-wide database curated by Andrea Belluscio (University of Rome, Italy) - see Telesca et al. (2015) for further details. A Random Forest (i.e. a very effective Machine Learning technique) was trained on data from regions where information was available and then used to predict the probability of occurrence of P. oceanica where needed. Please refer to Scardi et al. (2013) for full details of the methodology used. The maps show interim model outputs, which are likely to be improved with additional species occurrence data.

The data layers may be used (1) to guide cost-effective future survey efforts towards poorly sampled areas that are more likely to support these two habitats, (2) to inform marine spatial planning (including conservation planning), (3) to inform marine policy development, and (4) for initial screening as part of an environmental impact assessment. The data layer should not be used for spatial measures targeting fisheries, without prior groundtruthing.

Credits: "Giannoulaki M, Belluscio A, Colloca F, Fraschetti S, Scardi M, Smith C, Panayotidis P, Valavanis V, Spedicato MT (Eds.) (2013). Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH), final project report. DG MARE Specific Contract SI2.600741. Heraklion (Greece): Hellenic Centre for Marine Research. 557 p. URL: http://mareaproject.net/download/71 ; http://www.emodnetseabedhabitats.eu/default.aspx?page=1974","Telesca L, Belluscio A, Criscoli A, Ardizzone G, Apostolaki ET, Fraschetti S, Gristina M, Knittweis L, Martin CS, Pergent G, Alagna A, Badalamenti F, Garofalo G, Gerakaris V, Pace ML, Pergent-Martini C, Salomidi M. Seagrass meadows (Posidonia oceanica) distribution and trajectories of change. Scientific Reports 5: 12505. URL: http://www.nature.com/srep/2015/150728/srep12505/full/srep12505.html","Scardi M, Martin CS, Valavanis V, Fraschetti S, Belluscio A, Gristina M, Salomidi M, Punzo E, Panayotidis P, Giannoulaki M (2013). Task 1.3. Modelling of protected habitats using predictor variables. In: Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH), final project report (Eds. M Giannoulaki, A Belluscio, F Colloca, S Fraschetti, M Scardi, C Smith, P Panayotidis, V Valavanis, MT Spedicato). DG - MARE, specific contract SI2.600741. Heraklion (Greece): Hellenic Centre for Marine Research. 557pp."]</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>2313492ed3620164bab40534ac956aa88f7b9258</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution - Historical distribution (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Historical data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Historical Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean Sea from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>bfb190476af7917c4cd38027a52dbcb890874d98</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution - Historical Distribution (polygons)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Historical data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Historical Posidonia oceanica distribution (polygons) in the Mediterranean Sea from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b50f5d23ca3a892445f73aa5a13da664c0c2a1a5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Posidonia oceanica meadows distribution - Coastline of No Data (line)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Posidonia oceanica</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastline with unknown distribution of Posidonia oceanica meadows from dataset Seagrass beds distribution along the Mediterranean coasts - Mediterranean Sensitive Habitats (MEDISEH). The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>833627ae29a125bfcbbf301d96cd1327bfc43009</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Metridia lucens masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>met_luc_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Metridia lucens. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>5ebc0cfdd5cf965ac324b3d71d58612fb9d86f2c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Zostera marina beds distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Zostera marina</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Zostera marina beds distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean Sea. The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>65b768e5829e624fee72cbf0c473872018fdd4df</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Zostera noltii beds distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Zostera noltii</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Zostera noltii beds distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean Sea.The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>963f351c3c1bf092a99b6981faddc47d67038a84</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Ruppia cirrhosa beds distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Ruppia cirrhosa</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Angiosperms</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Ruppia cirrhosa beds distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean Sea. The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b924775b1e317a2633f50b62ef3772c0d53a33c2</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Ruppia maritima beds distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Ruppia maritima</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Ruppia maritima</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Ruppia maritima</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Ruppia maritima beds distribution (presence points) in the Mediterranean Sea. The dataset of seagrasses distribution across the Mediterranean produced in the framework of MEDISEH derived from the compilation of published and unpublished information.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>276d609e72febd1c5bf13d7d9e11e3951aa32216</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Tsunamis Affected Coast Points (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>tsunami_pt2_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Locations of coasts affected by tsunamis of unknown origin, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. In order to allow representation of different events, affected coasts are represented by points located in an average position for each event. Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>0b0462325071f2d65739d806a8a708a3e48edc8b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Terrace - lines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-TerracePL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Terraces are defined as a step-like landform and can be sub-divided thus:
1. Marine (1a: erosional / 1b: depositional); 2. Fluvial (2a: erosional / 2b: depositional); 3. Lacustrine (3a: erosional / 3b: depositional); 4. Other.

Further information on genesis of the terrace e.g. Erosional (e.g. wave-cut platform), Depositional (e.g. fluvial margins) is presented if known.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c0d2cbae8ac404c321d802ff4e3be8d83329766f</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Rock Peg Vein (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>rock_peg_vein_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Compiled by GSI. Geological Survey of Ireland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>214df36aab3ff3a431e2abe0474bb17142a0d2b7</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Thickness of Post-LGM Deposit</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>LastGlacialMaximum-ThicknessPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thickness of the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) deposit. Contours are presented as depth (metres) below present seafloor or the base of the post LGM sedimentary cover. LGM is defined on average at 18,000 years BP. In glaciated regions the thickness of the Holocene is used.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control.
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only, 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>611d9a3c2d25646d8541d528cc57b20373b167cd</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submerged Forest - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-SubmergedForestPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submerged forest is defined as the in situ remains of trees (especially tree stumps) that now lie submerged beneath a bay, sea, ocean, lake, or other body of water.

Chronological information on method used (e.g. dendrochronology, radiocarbon dating, based on indirect evidence etc.) and age as calendar age BP is included where known.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>23c15a81172e05a6e8149a14244e31b3abdd6acc</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Marine Hydrocarbons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine_hydrocarbons_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Hydrocarbons are organic compounds, formed over millions of years occurring mainly in sedimentary basins. The most common types of hydrocarbons are petroleum, natural gas, coal and bitumen. “Hydrocarbons provide the major part of the energy for modern civilisation, providing power for heating, lighting telecommunications, industry and agriculture machines as well as all forms of transport and also provide the raw material for numerous products ranging from plastics to fertilisers”. (Global Non-Living Resources on the Extended Continental Shelf: Prospects at the Year 2000. ISA Technical Study: No.1) Oil and natural gas are hydrocarbon reservoirs that occur naturally within thick sedimentary sequences. These are largely confined to the continental shelves, continental slopes, continental rises, and small ocean basins.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>83ee2bd512b2cc98e90898a1ea3f1ccc6ee54a37</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Seabed Substrates 1:250k Seabed Substrates 1:250k Seabed Substrates 1:250k</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_250k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_250k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_250k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1: 250 000 scale (250k). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology project started in 2013 with 36 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate map was produced October 2016.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1: 250 000 scale (250k). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology project started in 2013 with 36 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate map was produced October 2016.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1: 250 000 scale (250k). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology project started in 2013 with 36 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate map was produced October 2016.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>2e36f47eccfc3ec017112f1e4b4cac8ffb430a42</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Subaerial Landslide - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-SubaerialLandslidePG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Relict subaerial landslide feature. Where information is available these are subdivided further: 1. Slide deposit; 2. Slide scar (area of missing material on failure surface; 3. Other.

Where information on the genesis is available that is also provided:
1. Rotational; 2. Translational; 3. Block; 4. Rockfall; 5. Debris Flow; 6. Creep; 7. Lateral Spread; 8. Debris avalanche; 9. Other.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>aeb63e4656b9af6580e7169ff7fe6e8377b4d08f</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal and Submarine Springs</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Coastal_Submarine-SpringsPoint</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastal and submarine springs subdivided as:
1. Coastal; 2. Submarine; 3. Other.

Where information on the genesis of the feature is available that is also given e.g. geological fault (FEA_GEN_TY). The rate of flow in m3 / second is specified if known.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b475e4308f026e4cdbcda5feae28e41b31525639</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Borehole Index</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>borehole_index</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>boreholes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>grab samples</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>true ground</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>This data set is a compilation of all known marine points with geological knowledge. From this index, you can get an overview on available geological knowledge for European seas together with contact information for further details.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c87359ed1d9472602689237b7e99fd62f89c9428</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Marine Placers</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine_placers_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on marine placer deposits. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of known deposits and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. The placer deposit information presented here are locations with concentrations of detrital heavy metallic minerals or gemstones. The occurrences of such deposits are generally limited to the continental shelf regions less than 120m deep.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>376300fb451c7a8b2b4ba3cf3fb6a16bd4a5fc46</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Seabed Substrates 1:1M Seabed Substrates 1:1M Seabed Substrates 1:1M</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_1m</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_1m</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_1m</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Seabed substrate map of the European sea areas (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Barents Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, the White Sea, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1: 1 000 000 scale (1M). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology project.

The map is collated from the 1M data from Partners and generalized 1:250k EMODnet data. Where necessary, the existing substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme consists of altogether five seabed substrate classes.

Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available. The seabed substrate map was produced October 2016.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. overlays, topological gaps and data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European sea areas (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Barents Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, the White Sea, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1: 1 000 000 scale (1M). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology project.

The map is collated from the 1M data from Partners and generalized 1:250k EMODnet data. Where necessary, the existing substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme consists of altogether five seabed substrate classes.

Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available. The seabed substrate map was produced October 2016.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. overlays, topological gaps and data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European sea areas (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Barents Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, the White Sea, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1: 1 000 000 scale (1M). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology project.

The map is collated from the 1M data from Partners and generalized 1:250k EMODnet data. Where necessary, the existing substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme consists of altogether five seabed substrate classes.

Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available. The seabed substrate map was produced October 2016.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. overlays, topological gaps and data discontinuities.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f60a479f1d8dda1e8ccdcdde6ed04c976ca3a6c0</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Karst - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-KarstPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastal landscape underlain by limestone which has been eroded by dissolution, producing ridges, towers, fissures, sinkholes and other characteristic landforms. Where known the type of karst e.g. limestone, dolomite, evaporitic rocks, sinkholes, boulder piles etc. is stated.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f3b66878fea5db384f71259183c67ab395d2d523</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Subaerial Landslide - lines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-SubaerialLandslidePL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>No features yet.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>918e92f20488e00990122a0fa5c55fea19c27faa</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Phosphorites (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>phosphorites_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on phosphorite deposits. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of mapped deposits and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. Phosphorite deposits are found in sedimentary rocks, sufficiently rich in phosphate minerals. Phospherites are authigenic mineral deposits, formed in situ on the sea floor; they generally occur in deeper waters than placer deposits and are primarily used in the phosphate fertiliser industry.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>1d9981a04cdb7a4de4f1f15a0926d504a9bf352c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Phosphorites</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>phosphorites_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on phosphorite deposits. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of mapped deposits and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. Phosphorite deposits are found in sedimentary rocks, sufficiently rich in phosphate minerals. Phospherites are authigenic mineral deposits, formed in situ on the sea floor; they generally occur in deeper waters than placer deposits and are primarily used in the phosphate fertiliser industry.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4219834b6f57617f6456438f9a552fd2301e2007</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Aggregates</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>marine_aggregates_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Marine aggregates comprise near-shore deposits of non-metallic detrital minerals and calcium carbonate. They occur both on beaches and on deeper seabed areas and are principally mined for use in the construction industry. Concentrated into their present occurrences by hydrodynamic processes, aggregates may have originally been deposited by mechanisms such as river or glacial deposition.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8c23b4cf96bf545c251ae7a0de48fae4cb95d85a</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (40k-80k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_40k_80k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b2e498f0db7857467e683467670ed714d15a7d29</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Marine Sapropel (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine_sapropel_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Compiled by GSI. Geological Survey of Ireland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>fe5bfdb092407a3a222bd62f1b802ef4148ba202</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Aggregates (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine_aggregates_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The aggregate deposits presented here comprise near-shore deposits of non-metallic detrital minerals and calcium carbonate. They occur both on beaches and deeper seabed areas. Marine aggregate deposits are principally extracted for use in the construction industry. Concentrated into their present occurrences by hydrodynamic processes, aggregates may have originally been deposited by mechanisms such as river or glacial deposition.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>6952fe2dc7c43b01d32388876b12bbcce4d3df7d</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Evaporites</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>evaporites_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Evaporites are crystalline sedimentary rocks that form by the evaporation of natural brines. Having complex mineralogy, there are many varieties of evaporites; the most economically important minerals include: calcite, gypsum, anhydrite, halite, polyhalite, sylvite, carnallite, kainite, kieserite and anhydrite. Although evaporite deposits formed in ancient marine basins are extensive on land, many of these also extend beneath the sea, not only beneath the continental shelves but also under some marginal ocean basins. Present day occurrences of subsea anhydrite, potash and magnesium evaporite deposits have been described along the margins of the Mediterranean Sea as well as in the North Sea and West Baltic Sea.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8b3aa495841e9fdbb5a2040289622c036e2b3931</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (650k-1250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_650k_1250k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c12369240c9e64f852c24aa5830d60ab1906dcc1</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Seabed Substrate Map 1:50k Seabed Substrate Map 1:50k Seabed Substrate Map 1:50k</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_multiscale_50k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_multiscale_50k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_multiscale_50k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at various scales (50k, 100k, 250k, 1M). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology III project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology III project started in 2017 with 39 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate multiscale map was produced in March 2019.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at various scales (50k, 100k, 250k, 1M). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology III project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology III project started in 2017 with 39 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate multiscale map was produced in March 2019.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at various scales (50k, 100k, 250k, 1M). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology III project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology III project started in 2017 with 39 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate multiscale map was produced in March 2019.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f1d513edf6d9e5a7059750832ae208e4fac5c29f</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submerged Peat</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>SubmergedPeatPoint</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submerged accumulation of partially decayed vegetation or organic matter. 

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only, 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>eefa2e56ab2c848359e1eea720b6c2a4557f82c8</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Volcanoes Polygons (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>volcanic_center_pol_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submarine volcanic structures and eruption centers including hydrothermal activity, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Locally polygons are extended on land to include the emerged portions of the volcanoes. Polygons represent areas larger than 4 hectares. (for smaller areas, see volcanoes points layer) Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>147a7d854cfa66fe86ce7631afc1e395e6822a54</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>LGM Landscape - Base Post-LGM Deposit</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>LastGlacialMaximumPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) landscape / base of the post-LGM deposit. Contours are presented as depth (metres) below present mean sea level of the post LGM sedimentary cover. This is an erosional unconformity, where an infilled valley is present the valley base has been used. LGM defined on average at 18,000 years BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only, 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>dda3097c208bbc36851ba218755fa2006322ddb9</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Estuary - lines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-EstuaryPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The work package aimed to compile and harmonise available information on submerged landscape features by integrating existing records of palaeoenvironmental indicators with interpretations of geomorphology, stratigraphy and type of sediment.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c7b53704-999d-4721-b1a3-04ec60c87238</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Digital Bathymetry (DTM 2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>/Physical Environment/Bathymetry/Digital Terrain Model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Elevation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Administration and dimensions</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Terrestrial</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Gravity, magnetics and bathymetry</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Bathymetry and Elevation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Reference numbers</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Metadata parameters</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>EMODnet</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seafloor depth</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ocean depth</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Digital Terrain Model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>DTM</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>grid</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>bathymetric data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>European seas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Azores</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Madeira</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Canary Islands</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North-East Atlantic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Bay of Biscay</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Celtic Seas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>English Channel</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Norvegian Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Iceland Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Baltic Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Adriatic Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Aegean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Black Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Seabed</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Bathymetry</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>elevation</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>GeoTIFF</dc:format>
      <dc:format>NetCDF</dc:format>
      <dc:format>XYZ File</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The "EMODnet Digital Bathymetry (DTM)" is a multilayer bathymetric product for Europe’s sea basins covering::
• the Greater North Sea, including the Kattegat and stretches of water such as Fair Isle, Cromarty, Forth, Forties, Dover, Wight, and Portland
• the English Channel and Celtic Seas
• Western and Central Mediterranean Sea and Ionian Sea
• Bay of Biscay, Iberian coast and North-East Atlantic
• Adriatic Sea
• Aegean - Levantine Sea (Eastern Mediterranean)
• Azores - Madeira EEZ
• Canary Islands
• Baltic Sea
• Black Sea
• Norwegian – Icelandic seas

The DTM is based upon more than 7700 bathymetric survey data sets and Composite DTMs that have been gathered from 27 data providers from 18 European countries and involving 169 data originators. The gathered survey data sets can be discovered and requested for access through the Common Data Index (CDI) data discovery and access service that also contains additional European survey data sets for global waters. The Composite DTMs can be discovered through the Sextant Catalogue service. Both discovery services make use of SeaDataNet standards and services and have been integrated in the EMODnet Bathymetry web portal (http://www.emodnet-bathymetry.eu). In addition, the Bathymetry Viewing and Download service of the EMODnet bathymetry portal gives users wide functionality for viewing and downloading the EMODnet digital bathymetry such as:
• water depth (refering to the Lowest Astronomical Tide Datum - LAT) in gridded form 
on a DTM grid of 1/8 * 1/8 arc minute of longitude and latitude (ca 230 * 230 meters)
• option to view depth parameters of individual DTM cells and references to source data
• option to download DTM in 16 tiles in different formats: ESRI ASCII, XYZ, EMODnet CSV, NetCDF (CF), GeoTiff and SD
• layer with a number of high resolution DTMs for coastal regions
• layer with wrecks from the UKHO Wrecks database.
The NetCDF (CF) DTM files are fit for use in a special 3D Viewer software package which is based on the existing open source NASA World Wind JSK application. It has been developed in the frame of the EU FP7 Geo-Seas project (another sibling of SeaDataNet for marine geological and geophysical data) and is freely available. The 3D viewer also supports the ingestion of WMS overlay maps. The SD files can also be used for 3D viewing by means of the freely available iView4De(Fledermaus) software.

The original datasets themselves are not distributed but described in the metadata services, giving clear information about the background survey data used for the DTM, their access restrictions, originators and distributors and facilitating requests by users to originator.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>3d50b33e1473ba443fe094ed63073fb2236e60b4</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Volcanoes Lines (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>volcanic_center_lin_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submarine volcanic structures and eruption centers, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Lines represent eruptive fissures or borders of lava flows. Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>ecb22f233db3b5c3dfbe94939df786605a2cac3c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Landslides Polygons (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>landslide_pol_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submarine landslides, detected on the seabed, outcropping or buried, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Locally polygons are extended on land to include the subaerial portions and/or origin of the landslides. Polygons represent areas larger than 4 hectares. (for smaller areas, see submarine landslides points layer) Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>2fcf85a568a4db10c58ef603510dcf7ea3e8cdb4</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Gas Hydrates (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>gas_hydrates_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information of known gas hydrate deposits in European waters. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of mapped deposits and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. The information presented here are for mapped gas hydrates deposits. These deposits are typically formed in stable solid state; they are mostly composed of methane (CH4), surrounded by water molecules and are generally found at continental margins.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>3f85907b433f313915dd1ea902d05bc39d2e72c1</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Wetlands</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-WetlandsPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Areas of relict wetland. Where known the type of wetland is included e.g. salt marsh, tidal flat, peat bog, supra tidal zone, swamp, other.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>2e334f654d9d499794182149a600acab71d3bcaf</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Metal Rich Sediments (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>metal_rich_sediments_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Compiled by GSI. Geological Survey of Ireland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>65c5c8f5b05f066d7233b0f1367abcae550bbcf6</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (3M-100M)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_3m_100m</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>e861d1605d55c93afd1efd9379ce9bb368bf8531</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Landslides Points (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>landslide_pt_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submarine landslides, detected on the seabed, outcropping or buried, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Points represent landslide areas smaller than 4 hectares. (for larger areas, see submarine landslides polygons layer) Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>6331ab919a8b45a9e8c51b6ca5d2febf55d4ac42</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Channel - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ChannelPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Channel landscape features subdivided where possible into open tunnel valley, open fluvial channel, open tidal channel, tidal inlet, buried fluvial channel, buried tunnel valley, or buried tidal channel. 

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP. Confidence is defined as follows: 

1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>dbc9fa6ee3c53664fb990db45aa7ef7fc316bde4</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Polymetallic Sulphides</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>polymetallic_sulphides_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 Minerals leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on Polymetallic sulphides PMS. EMODnet partners are submitting mapped PMS locations and existing information, here you can view data collated thus far. The PMS information presented here are of mapped PMS locations. Also known as Volcanogenic Massive Sulfides (VMS), Seafloor Massive Sulfides (SMS) and Black Smokers, PMS are base metal sulfur-rich mineral deposits. They occur along the earth’s major tectonic belts at spreading centres, as well as in intraplate regions where islands and seamounts are formed.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>bf941c5bd26b57a02b0b8675408765c97f8a5ce8</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Sea-floor Pre-Quaternary Bedrock Geology</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>pre_quaternary_poly</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Pre-Quaternary -age
This web map service shows the chronostratigraphic age of geological units of the seafloor originated earlier than 2,588 Ma from now (pre-Quaternary). International Geological Map of Europe and Adjacent Areas (Asch, 2005). The scale varies between 25,000 and 5 000 000.
The data were compiled by BGR from the EMODnet geology partner organisations in the EMODnet Geology project phases I, II and III between 2009 and 2019. 

Pre-Quaternary  -lithology
This web map service shows the rock type (lithology) of geological units of the seafloor originated earlier than 2,588 Ma from now (pre-Quaternary). International Geological Map of Europe and Adjacent Areas (Asch, 2005). 
The scale varies between 25 000 and 5 000 000.
The data were compiled by BGR from the EMODnet geology partner organisations in the EMODnet Geology project phases I, II and III between 2009 and 2019. 
The scale varies between 25 000 and 5 000 000.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>0b83a235b5754ae595c7d2a91b0add858b2d3973</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Ratio of large to small copepods masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>ratio_large_to_small_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded map of the large to small copepods ratio. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>052fd06e20cf01d328a081b40ccb4b8aaf68c31b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Temora longicornis masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>tem_lon_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Temora longicornis. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>33388e9718d07e8171ea43735e71e549f0173231</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance large copepods masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>tot_lar_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded map of the relative abundance of large copepods. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b1d3b444a111c94e69e6853a83957f1d2ebaa387</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance small copepods masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>tot_sma_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded map of the relative abundance of small copepods. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>57da19477311bdfb0e7845d43da18bdc65382ae9</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Relative abundance Oithona spp. masked with relative error 0.3 (North Atlantic, 1958-2016)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>oit_spp_19582016_L1_err</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>WCS</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ImageMosaic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Gridded abundance map of Oithona spp. This product was developed with DIVA (Data-Interpolating Variational Analysis). Data was provided by SAHFOS (Continuous Plankton Recorder) for use as an ICES operational oceanographic product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8ca217d24b8fd4118d61e6d7f7f859a3c614413e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Fluid Emissions Polygons (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>mud_volc_fluid_emis_pol_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Fluid emissions of non volcanic origin and mud-volcanoes on seafloors, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Polygons represent areas larger than 4 hectares. (for smaller areas, see fluid emissions points layer) Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a9e8dba1fe01a0c58f690b1ec58deac1e265c93c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Rock Peg Vein</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>rock_peg_vein_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Compiled by GSI. Geological Survey of Ireland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>335790e0d676535baf4fe6cfcc3a79cab5dac9bc</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submerged Forest - points</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-SubmergedForestPoints</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submerged forest is defined as the in situ remains of trees (especially tree stumps) that now lie submerged beneath a bay, sea, ocean, lake, or other body of water.

Chronological information on method used (e.g. dendrochronology, radiocarbon dating, based on indirect evidence etc.) and age as calendar age BP is included where known.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>8966f2185775edeacc4eeaf748b728bbc48f7331</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Earthquakes Points (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>earthquakes_pt_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Locations of relevant events delivered by National Partners and not reported on the Seismic Portal (EMSC website).</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>84f756bb884ad5356df00d1f672b2326f8bae444</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Polymetallic Nodules</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>polymetallic_nodules_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on Polumetallic nodules. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of mapped polymetallic nodules and existing information; here you can view data collated thus far. The information presented here are of mapped extents of polymetallic nodules within participating surveys national EEZ. Polymetallic nodules are also known as manganese nodules. These ferromanganese concretions comprise mainly iron and ferromanganese oxides, with accessory minerals such as cobalt, copper and nickel, zinc, vanadium, platinum and molybdenum.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a491d0ece96bae9d12c07b40da7029077c2a678c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Tsunamis Origin Points (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>tsunami_pt_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Locations of events which originated tsunamis, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Wherever possible, connected events reported in other EMODnet Geology layers are indicated in the Attribute table. Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>9bdb6777ff1e56c10401904091ca2d0f1856a287</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Sea-floor Quaternary Geology</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>quaternary_poly</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Quaternary –age
This web map service shows the chronostratigraphic age of geological units of the seafloor originated in the Quaternary period (i.e.  2,588 Ma from now until today). 
The data were compiled by BGR from the EMODnet geology partner organisations in the EMODnet Geology project phases II and III between 2009 and 2019.
The scale varies between 20 000 and 2 500 000.


Quaternary  -lithology
This web map service shows the rock type (lithology) of geological units of the seafloor originated in the Quaternary period (i.e.  2,588 Ma from now until today).
The data were compiled by BGR from the EMODnet geology partner organisations in the EMODnet Geology project phases I, II and III between 2009 and 2019.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a52ca2d9f2c582616b7ad55fce77aa7dfd69bfed</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal Landforms - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandformPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastal Landforms created during periods of lower sea level. These features may or may not be submerged today (e.g. as a result of isostatic rebound). Where possible these have been subdivided into the type of Coastal Landform e.g. Beachrock, Littoral deposit, Coastal dunes, Cliff, Sand bars, beach ridges, Other.

Where information is available on the genesis of the beach deposit this has been provided, e.g. foreshore sediment, aeolian sediment (e.g. dunes).

Where information on sediment grain size and composition is available this has been provided. Uncemented/cemented (e.g. beach rock).

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>93bb06e62e0fe8522e8dd481f65c4f8d2b5cbe5e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Delta - lines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-DeltaPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Polyline defining the margin of a former delta. A delta is formed by deposition of sediment transported via river as it enters slower-moving / stagnant body of water such as a marine environment, lake or estuary.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>54a32436b55b30a6dcb1739b071ce80fed44226c</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (1250k-3M)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_1250k_3m</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>96d71e92a4751bf7ee38f6c79fbe5d664713d922</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Gas Hydrates</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>gas_hydrates_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information of known gas hydrate deposits in European waters. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of mapped deposits and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. The information presented here are for mapped gas hydrates deposits. These deposits are typically formed in stable solid state; they are mostly composed of methane (CH4), surrounded by water molecules and are generally found at continental margins.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>0f9fdba05239515f8bd79a5fea356fb32d01552a</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>cofe_rich_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts. EMODnet partners are submitting the mapped extent of cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. Cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts are metallic mineral deposits that often form at depths between 400 to 4000 metres, as thin layers on the flanks of seamounts and submarine volcanoes. The crusts accumulate when manganese, iron and trace metals including cobalt, copper, nickel and platinum dissolved in sea water are precipitated onto the volcanic substrate.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>394012816f6eb26ac8d0cfed65a29810087262cf</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Tsunamis Affected Coast Points (250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>tsunami_pt2_250k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Locations of the main points along the coasts affected by tsunamis whose origin is unknown, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Note: Project is ongoing and the work is in progress; blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>3c7ab02716822d744dcefd8662fa12f108053a5e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (450k-650k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_450k_650k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c43a498ff76cabd93ceeec315b1211e469443d17</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Archaeological Feature - polygon</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ArchaeologicalGeomorphologicalPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submerged archaeological sites subdivided as: 

1. Cave site; 
2. Open air site; 
3. Settlement; 
4. Other. 

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP. 

Confidence is defined as follows: 

1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>5af62d288bc2eba646fc86f430c22a881bf89a25</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Palaeocoastline</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Coastline-PalaeocoastlinePL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Palaeocoastline polyline features delineating former coastlines and shorelines subdivided into those which have been mapped (direct observation) or modelled.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only, 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>20a9ec0d7c352c6805ac0242147fbdfd5ff4fc43</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Lake</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-LakePG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Former lake landform. Where information on the genesis of the feature is available (e.g. dammed glacial lake) this has been included.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4a7b98cc303956b0038bbfded8024dd9277de791</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Sea Level Index Point</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Sealevel-IndexPoints</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Primary and Secondary Sea Level Index Points. Where information is available on the genesis of the index point it is given.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only, 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>1ee9585d92f0fbe63503065933245b4d5e783c72</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Subaerial Landslide - points</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-SubaerialLandslidePoints</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>No features yet.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>634ed41193a810230715929aee934e13189a13cd</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Geological Event Distribution</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>geological_event_distribution</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Geological Event Distribution</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>dataprovider@Italian National Institute for Environmental Protection and Research</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>DS_TOPIC@geoscientificinformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>continent@Europe</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Index map of all European seas reporting areas of occurrence, no occurrence and no data for each kind of event in every sea. Representation refers to the item Landslide. In order to obtain information on the distribution of other events click on the polygon of your interest to visualize the attributes of other items.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>b49ec64935af6801dcdaf6946e136c21f87a941b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Lagoon</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-LagoonPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Relict lagoon coastal landform defined as a shallow body of water separated from a larger body of water by barrier islands or reefs. 

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c04867cee3fef2040a1f244e07a36e33acbbda17</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (250k-350k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_250k_350k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>0b6e441a4574e578ea1d8b65a42a52ae726b7fc2</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Evaporites (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>evaporites_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Evaporites are crystalline sedimentary rocks that form by the evaporation of natural brines. Having complex mineralogy, there are many varieties of evaporites; the most economically important minerals include: calcite, gypsum, anhydrite, halite, polyhalite, sylvite, carnallite, kainite, kieserite and anhydrite. Although evaporite deposits formed in ancient marine basins are extensive on land, many of these also extend beneath the sea, not only beneath the continental shelves but also under some marginal ocean basins. Present day occurrences of subsea anhydrite, potash and magnesium evaporite deposits have been described along the margins of the Mediterranean Sea as well as in the North Sea and West Baltic Sea.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f02027dc1812101f26086b3ddd0b34479e1964a3</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Marine Sapropel</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>marine_sapropel_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Compiled by GSI. Geological Survey of Ireland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>9d17aaa54f513d18a14b5dd45dec42121216f750</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>cofe_rich_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>EMODnet</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Geology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Minerals</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Cobalt</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>rich</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ferromanganese</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>crusts</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>metallic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>deposits</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts. EMODnet partners are submitting the mapped extent of cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. Cobalt rich ferromanganese crusts are metallic mineral deposits that often form at depths between 400 to 4000 metres, as thin layers on the flanks of seamounts and submarine volcanoes. The crusts accumulate when manganese, iron and trace metals including cobalt, copper, nickel and platinum dissolved in sea water are precipitated onto the volcanic substrate.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>c49378e9d567f2dea09e9da35692b4b3387cec14</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Metal Rich Sediments</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>metal_rich_sediments_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Compiled by GSI. Geological Survey of Ireland.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>07f550ad6692ff518d96de8817a114a9fa1b5c19</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Sea-floor Pre-quaternary Faults</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>pre_quaternary_line</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>This web map service shows faults and structures of geological units of the seafloor originated earlier than 2,588 Ma from now (pre-Quaternary). 
The data were compiled by BGR from the EMODnet geology partner organisations in the EMODnet Geology project phases I, II and III between 2009 and 2019 and the International Geological Map of Europe and Adjacent Areas (Asch, 2005). 
The scale varies between 1:200 000 and 1:5 000 000</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>070d9c68c1a7bfabfe033f313f5e275945c9830e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Marine Placers (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine_placers_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on marine placer deposits. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of known deposits and established information; here you can view data collated thus far. The placer deposit information presented here are locations with concentrations of detrital heavy metallic minerals or gemstones. The occurrences of such deposits are generally limited to the continental shelf regions less than 120m deep.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>149c4a1237023094c30facea65f261153e43e821</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Delta - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-DeltaPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Delta	Relict delta landform formed by deposition of sediment transported via river as it enters slower-moving / stagnant body of water such as a marine environment, lake or estuary.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>7770b54e17aa8da9645955ffd9bf3a3d77f103b6</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (350k-450k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_350k_450k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>43104c34cb25ac6021f17846d5dabd87c45cf17d</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Quaternary Tectonics Lines (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>tectonics_lin_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Quaternary submarine tectonic lines in geologically active areas, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>86f7f9aad89086b9a3b4ea84f60b8329e88c15b9</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The shoreline is a highly dynamic land-sea interface that provides important services such as ecology, flood
protection and recreation. It is constantly modified by wind, waves and tides, and impacted by human activity.
Hence, the decadal change of shorelines reflect natural processes as well as human influence, whether positive
or negative. Climatic-driven changes such as sea level rise, higher waves and changes in wind direction put
increasing pressure on many of Europe’s shorelines.
Knowing how, and at what rate, our coasts are changing is the first step to successfully managing them. The
new EMODnet Geology shoreline-migration map, released today, allows users to visualise pan-European coastal
behaviour for 2007-2017 at different spatial scales. A built-in search and zoom functionality allows online users
to distinguish areas of landward migration (erosion or submergence), stability, and seaward migration (accretion
or emergence). The underlying, downloadable satellite-based dataset offers additional information on annual
values and uncertainty.
With the new map, international policy makers can determine large-scale coastal vulnerability while national
and regional coastal managers are able to fill existing gaps in field-monitoring data and to identify potential
areas of rapid change. The map also provides the general public with a useful insight into one of Europe’s most
obvious climate-change effects. Most importantly, scientists may explain spatial patterns and provide feedback
on methodological advantages as well as shortcomings, thus helping to optimise the big-data methodology
used.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>fb90343eeca6f2cc17201460bc9fbd1b00fc68c8</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Archaeological Feature - point</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ArchaeologicalPoint</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submerged archaeological sites subdivided as: 

1. Cave site; 
2. Open air site; 
3. Settlement; 
4. Other. 

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP. 

Confidence is defined as follows: 

1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>f4bd50711ab7e76fafd7b48fbc171b68fb459b82</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (80k-150k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_80k_150k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>85855bf3e82e2630d097046f03079be3ae52738d</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Marine Hydrocarbons (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>marine_hydrocarbons_point_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Hydrocarbons are organic compounds, formed over millions of years occurring mainly in sedimentary basins. The most common types of hydrocarbons are petroleum, natural gas, coal and bitumen. “Hydrocarbons provide the major part of the energy for modern civilisation, providing power for heating, lighting telecommunications, industry and agriculture machines as well as all forms of transport and also provide the raw material for numerous products ranging from plastics to fertilisers”. (Global Non-Living Resources on the Extended Continental Shelf: Prospects at the Year 2000. ISA Technical Study: No.1) Oil and natural gas are hydrocarbon reservoirs that occur naturally within thick sedimentary sequences. These are largely confined to the continental shelves, continental slopes, continental rises, and small ocean basins.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>9fd435d3a0768f9c974a17c5fd543967c08b3fa1</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Karst - points</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-KarstPoints</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastal landscape underlain by limestone which has been eroded by dissolution. Where known this has been subdivided thus: 
1. Caves; 2. Sinkholes; 3. Solution pans; 4. Cockpits; 5. Karst cones; 6. Towers; 7. Boulder piles; 8. Tor; 9. Other.
Note that we are using the term ‘sinkhole’ to include dolines, cenotes and swallow holes.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>4fd35b26b780aa9752a834e5d62319015d9fb897</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (150k-250k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_150k_250k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>92ac815e31add46a7f39ad19b06354de1d981338</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Landslides Lines (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>landslide_lin_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submarine landslides scarps, detected on the seabed, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>e52e4a172bd04eb25a10f8bff2add00938fe65a2</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Palaeo-Alluvial Plain</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-PAlluvialPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>A palaeo-alluvial plain is defined as a largely flat landform created by the repeated deposition of alluvial sediments over a long period of time by running water. 

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>87570beece06fe2e06a69b599d63ba9b9c93e983</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal Landforms - lines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandformPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Coastal Landforms created during periods of lower sea level. These features may or may not be submerged today (e.g. as a result of isostatic rebound). Where possible these have been subdivided into the type of Coastal Landform e.g. Beachrock, Littoral deposit, Coastal dunes, Cliff, Sand bars, beach ridges, Other.

Where information is available on the genesis of the beach deposit this has been provided, e.g. foreshore sediment, aeolian sediment (e.g. dunes).

Where information on sediment grain size and composition is available this has been provided. Uncemented/cemented (e.g. beach rock).

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>9ce44607c1e7c9d75574a99596be4ca10adf367f</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Volcanoes Points (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>volcanic_center_pt_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Submarine volcanic structures and eruption centers including hydrothermal activity, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Points represent areas smaller than 4 hectares. (for larger areas, see volcanoes polygons layer) or additional culminations of volcanic structures. Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>47d24518347c67ee2686e89cb88a4c9bc18436f8</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Seabed Accumulation Rates</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_accumulation_rates</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Sedimentation rate map of the European Seas (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the North Sea, the Barents Sea, the sea around Iceland, the Iberian Coast, the Western Mediterranean Sea (within EU waters), the Adriatic Sea, the Ionian Sea and the Central Mediterranean Sea (within EU waters), the Aegean-Levantine Sea (within EU waters – including the Turkish sector) and the Black Sea.

The map is collated and compiled within the EMODnet-Geology project. Estimations of modern sedimentation rates (cm/year) are based mainly on the 137Cs and the 210Pb dating. The 137Cs could be used as a time-marker in the sediment column. In the sediment column the activity peak of 137Cs corresponds to the fallout of the Chernobyl nuclear power plant accident of April 1986. Some sedimentation rates were estimated from acoustic-seismic and sediment core data.

This version was produced October 10th, 2016.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>11376f289d093664cd4e67fd7646b4ba4c7b7973</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Terrace - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-TerracePG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Terraces are defined as a step-like landform and can be sub-divided thus:
1. Marine (1a: erosional / 1b: depositional); 2. Fluvial (2a: erosional / 2b: depositional); 3. Lacustrine (3a: erosional / 3b: depositional); 4. Other.

Further information on genesis of the terrace e.g. Erosional (e.g. wave-cut platform), Depositional (e.g. fluvial margins) is presented if known.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>cf5a00104e50c8bfaf88d70860316c2feb43a263</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Submarine Fluid Emissions Points (100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>mud_volc_fluid_emis_pt_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Fluid emissions of non volcanic origin and mud-volcanoes on seafloors, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Points represent areas smaller than 4 hectares. (for larger areas, see fluid emissions polygons layer) Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>21de9af53f7f1f610d69b9f6f5df1c6500b985f5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Estuary - polygons</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>CoastalLandform-EstuaryPG</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Relict estuary landform defined as a partially enclosed coastal body of brackish water with one or more rivers or streams flowing into it and a free connect to the open sea/ocean. Where know the type of estuary (e.g. fjord, estuary, ria) is included.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP.

Confidence is defined as follows:
1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>964ec38218a6b9296745ad56e76de32dc61fd042</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Coastal migration via satellite data (0-40k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>coastal_migration_2019_0_40k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Thanks to the public availability of satellite data (optical imagery of ESA Sentinel 2 and NASA Landsat 5, 7 &amp; 8 with pixel resolutions of 10-30 metres and a revisit time of 1 to 2 weeks) and new analytical tools for processing big data (such as the Google Earth Engine), the EMODnet Geology team in collaboration with Deltares and TNO (Geological Survey of the Netherlands) were able to look at shoreline migration in a new way. Scripts for automated detection of the land-water boundary were used to separate land from water in annual image composites for the period 2007-2017. During this process, data points were generated for each part along the European shoreline. These points were then averaged by year and analysed for a decadal period. 
Visualising pan-European shoreline change means making choices, like defining a stable shoreline for example. A mean rate of 0.5 metre per year was chosen, though this rate depends on the landscape: granite cliffs for example shows less decadal dynamics compared to a sandy barrier island.
The spatial resolution of the method, depending on the pixel resolution of the individual satellite images which is about 10 metres, is still limiting. Validations of abovementioned method have shown that the method is less accurate in case of bluffs, cliffs and muddy coasts, and as such further validations will need to take place. EMODnet Geology hopes that by releasing the satellite-based dataset now, coastal experts and other end users will be able to discover and communicate possibilities and limitations of automated methods for the extraction of shoreline position and quantification of annual to decadal change. To help in this process, a companion map showing shoreline migration on the basis of field data and expert is made available, thereby facilitating a first-order comparison.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>e2d4a1109505b49b7f2cb3b3099863526f45c725</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Sea-floor Geomorphology</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geomorphology</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The data were compiled by BGR from the EMODnet geology partner organisations in the EMODnet Geology project phase III between 2017 and 2019.

The scale varies between 10 000 and 5 000 000.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>bb24ba07ea01f9268b20ff8ad06f42aed6f37ec1</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Polymetallic Nodules (points)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>polymetallic_nodules_points_feb2019</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>The GSI, as partner and Work Package 7 (Minerals) leader of EMODnet Geology Phase II, are compiling information on Polumetallic nodules. EMODnet partners are submitting the spatial extent of mapped polymetallic nodules and existing information; here you can view data collated thus far. The information presented here are of mapped extents of polymetallic nodules within participating surveys national EEZ. Polymetallic nodules are also known as manganese nodules. These ferromanganese concretions comprise mainly iron and ferromanganese oxides, with accessory minerals such as cobalt, copper and nickel, zinc, vanadium, platinum and molybdenum.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a434a2bb3e860a1c5485124055c4458e7fdfe08b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Seabed Substrates 1:100k Seabed Substrates 1:100k Seabed Substrates 1:100k</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seabed_substrate_100k</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1:100 000 scale (100k). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology III project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology III project started in 2017 with 39 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate map was produced in March 2018.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1:100 000 scale (100k). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology III project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology III project started in 2017 with 39 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate map was produced in March 2018.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities. Seabed substrate map of the European marine areas including (e.g. the Baltic Sea, the Greater North Sea, the Celtic Sea, the Iberian Coast, and the Mediterranean Sea within EU waters) at 1:100 000 scale (100k). The map is collated and harmonized from seabed substrate information within the EMODnet-Geology III project.

Where necessary, the existing seabed substrate classifications (of individual maps) have been translated to a scheme that is supported by EUNIS. This EMODnet reclassification scheme includes at least five seabed substrate classes. Four substrate classes are defined on the basis of the modified Folk triangle (mud to sandy mud; sand; coarse sediment; and mixed sediment) and one additional substrate class (rock and boulders) was included by the project team. If the original seabed substrate dataset has enabled more detailed substrate classification, classifications with 7 and 16 substrate classes might be available.

The EMODnet-Geology III project started in 2017 with 39 marine departments of the geological surveys of Europe (from 30 countries), with an objective to assemble marine geological information from all European sea areas. The seabed substrate map was produced in March 2018.

Note: The data may include some errors e.g. data discontinuities.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>a992efe9c435fa84322571a2380c24bfec198a78</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Channel - lines</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ChannelPL</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>Polylines defining the channel thalweg and / or channel edge of buried or open features.

Chronological information is presented as calendar age BP. Confidence is defined as follows: 

1. High: Sampled feature with good age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
2. Sampled feature with poor or none age and palaeoenvironmental control. 
3. Constructed by remote sensing data only. 
4. Low: Reasonable without any direct evidence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>18ff0d48-b203-4a65-94a9-5fd8b0ec35f6</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet Digital Bathymetry (DTM 2018)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>/Physical Environment/Bathymetry/Digital Terrain Model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Elevation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Administration and dimensions</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Gravity, magnetics and bathymetry</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Terrestrial</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Bathymetry and Elevation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Reference numbers</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Metadata parameters</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>EMODnet</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>seafloor depth</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>ocean depth</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Digital Terrain Model</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>DTM</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>grid</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>bathymetric data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>European seas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Azores</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Madeira</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Canary Islands</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North-East Atlantic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Bay of Biscay</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Celtic Seas</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>English Channel</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>North Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Norvegian Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Iceland Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Baltic Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Mediterranean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Adriatic Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Aegean Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Black Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Arctic</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Barentz Sea</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Seabed</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Bathymetry</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>elevation</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>GeoTIFF</dc:format>
      <dc:format>NetCDF</dc:format>
      <dc:format>XYZ File</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>The "EMODnet Digital Bathymetry (DTM)- 2018" is a multilayer bathymetric product for Europe’s sea basins covering:
•  the Greater North Sea, including the Kattegat and stretches of water such as Fair Isle, Cromarty, Forth, Forties,Dover, Wight, and Portland 
•  the English Channel and Celtic Seas  
•  Western Mediterranean, the Ionian Sea and the Central Mediterranean Sea 
•  Iberian Coast and Bay of Biscay (Atlantic Ocean) 
•  Adriatic Sea (Mediterranean) 
•  Aegean - Levantine Sea (Mediterranean). 
•  Madeira and Azores (Macaronesia) 
•  Baltic Sea 
•  Black Sea 
•  Norwegian and Icelandic Seas 
•  Canary Islands (Macaronesia) 
•  Arctic region and Barentz Sea
The DTM is based upon more than 9400 bathymetric survey data sets and Composite DTMs that have been gathered from 49 data providers from 24 countries riparian to European seas. Also Satellite Derived Bathymetry data products have been included derived from Landsat 8 satellite images. The source reference layer in the portal viewing service gives metadata of the data sets used with their data providers; the metadata also acknowledges the data originators. The incorporated survey data sets itself can be discovered and requested for access through the Common Data Index (CDI) data discovery and access service that in September 2018 contained &gt; 27.000 survey data sets from European data providers for global waters. The Composite DTMs can be discovered through the Sextant Catalogue service. Both discovery services make use of SeaDataNet standards and services and have been integrated in the EMODnet Bathymetry web portal (http://www.emodnet-bathymetry.eu). In addition, the Bathymetry Viewing and Download service of the EMODnet bathymetry portal gives users wide functionality for viewing and downloading the EMODnet digital bathymetry such as:
• water depth (refering to the Lowest Astronomical Tide Datum - LAT) in gridded form on a DTM grid of 1/16 * 1/16 arc minute of longitude and latitude (ca 115 * 115 meters)
• option to view depth parameters of individual DTM cells and references to source data
• option to download DTM in 64 tiles in different formats: ESRI ASCII, XYZ, EMODnet CSV, NetCDF (CF), GeoTiff and SD
• option to visualize the DTM in 3D in the browser without plug-in
• layer with a number of high resolution DTMs for coastal regions
• layer with wrecks from the UKHO Wrecks database.
The EMODnet DTM is also available by means of OGC web services (WMS, WFS, WCS, WMTS), which are specified at the EMODnet Bathymetry portal.  
The original datasets themselves are not distributed but described in the metadata services, giving clear information about the background survey data used for the DTM, their access restrictions, originators and distributors and facilitating requests by users to originator.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>02a444c8-bd2d-4e15-8e69-806059103760</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EUSeaMap2 (2016) Broad-Scale Predictive Habitat Map</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Web Mapping Service</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Output of the 2016 EUSeaMap broad-scale predictive model, produced by EMODnet Seabed Habitats.

The extent of the mapped area includes the Mediterranean Sea, Black Sea, Baltic Sea, and areas of the North Eastern Atlantic extending from the Canary Islands in the south to Norway  in the North.

The map was produced using a "top-down" modelling approach using classified habitat descriptors to determine a final output habitat.

Habitat descriptors differ per region but include:
    Biological zone
    Energy class
    Oxygen regime
    Salinity regime
    Seabed Substrate
    Riverine input

Habitat descriptors (excepting Substrate) are calculated using underlying physical data and thresholds derived from statistical analyses or expert judgement on known conditions.

The model is produced in Arc Model Builder (10.1). 

The model was created using raster input layers with a cell size of 0.002dd (roughly 250 meters). The model includes the sublittoral zone only; due to the high variability of the littoral zone, a lack of detailed substrate data and the resolution of the model, it is difficult to predict littoral habitats at this scale.

The map follows the EUNIS 2007-11 classification system where it is appropriate.
For details on methodology see:
Populus J. And Vasquez M. (Eds), 2017. EUSeaMap, a European broad-scale seabed habitat map. Ifremer
Available from: http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00388/49975/</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>39b23bdb-1f0b-412f-9746-bd816bb9c11e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EUSeaMap2 (2016) Broad-Scale Predictive Habitat Map - Confidence</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Web Mapping Service</dc:format>
      <dc:relation>02a444c8-bd2d-4e15-8e69-806059103760</dc:relation>
      <dct:modified>2017-06-12</dct:modified>
      <dct:abstract>Confidence in the full output of the 2016 EUSeaMap broad-scale predictive model, produced by EMODnet Seabed Habitats.

Values are on a range from 1 (Low confidence) to 3 (High confidence).

Confidence is calculated by amalgamating the confidence values of the underlying applicable habitat descriptors used to generate the habitat value in the area in question.

Habitat descriptors differ per region but include:
    Biological zone
    Energy class
    Oxygen regime
    Salinity regime
    Seabed Substrate
    Riverine input

Confidence in habitat descriptors are driven by the confidence in the source data used to determine the descriptor, and the confidence in the threshold/margin (areas closer to a boundary between two classes will have lower confidence). For each grid cell, the confidence in final habitat class was the minimum of all relevant habitat descriptor confidence scores.
Confidence values are also available for each habitat descriptor and input data layer.

It is important to note that a habitat type confidence score is only relevant to that particular level of the classification system. For example, a cell of A3.1 high energy infralittoral rock with ‘low’ energy class confidence, ‘moderate’ biozone confidence and ‘high’ substrate type confidence would have an overall ‘low’ confidence. However, moving up the hierarchy to EUNIS level two (A3 infralittoral rock) removes the energy class; therefore, the confidence of the EUNIS level two habitat type would only consider the ‘moderate’ biozone confidence and ‘high’ substrate type confidence, resulting in an overall ‘moderate’ confidence.

For details on methodology see:
Populus J. And Vasquez M. (Eds), 2017. EUSeaMap, a European broad-scale seabed habitat map. Ifremer
Available from: http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00388/49975/</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>d23d0516-6ff4-4fb8-bf78-c11991cef78b</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EUSeaMap2 (2016) Broad-Scale Predictive Habitat Map - MSFD Benthic Broad Habitat Types</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Marine Strategy Framework Directive</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Predominant habitats</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>environment</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Web Mapping Service</dc:format>
      <dc:relation>02a444c8-bd2d-4e15-8e69-806059103760</dc:relation>
      <dct:abstract>Output of the 2016 EUSeaMap broad-scale predictive model, produced by EMODnet Seabed Habitats and aggregated into the Benthic Broad Habitat Types of the Marine Strategy Framework Directive (as defined in the Commission Decision 17 May 2017).

The extent of the mapped area includes the Mediterranean Sea, Black Sea, Baltic Sea, and areas of the North Eastern Atlantic extending from the Canary Islands in the south to Norway and Iceland in the North.

The map was produced using a "top-down" modelling approach using classified habitat descriptors to determine a final output habitat.

Habitat descriptors differ per region but include:
    Biological zone
    Energy class
    Oxygen regime
    Salinity regime
    Seabed Substrate
    Riverine input

Habitat descriptors (excepting Substrate) are calculated using underlying physical data and thresholds derived from statistical analyses or expert judgement on known conditions.

The model is produced in Arc Model Builder (10.1). For more information on the modelling process please read the EMODnet Seabed Habitats Technical report (See Online Resources)

The model was created using raster input layers with a cell size of 0.002dd (roughly 250 meters). The model includes the sublittoral zone only; due to the high variability of the littoral zone, a lack of detailed substrate data and the resolution of the model, it is difficult to predict littoral habitats at this scale.

For details on methodology see:
Populus J. And Vasquez M. (Eds), 2017. EUSeaMap, a European broad-scale seabed habitat map. Ifremer
Available from: http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00388/49975/</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>39746d9c-4220-425c-bc26-7cb3056c36a5</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Areal Extent of Seagrass Meadows (Essential Ocean Variable)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>This layer shows the current known extent of Seagrass meadows in European waters, collated by EMODnet Seabed Habitats. Seagrasses provide essential habitat and nursery areas for many marine fauna. There are approximately 72 seagrass species that belong to four major groups: Zosteraceae, Hydrocharitaceae, Posidoniaceae and Cymodoceaceae. Zostera beds and Cymodecea meadows are named on the OSPAR Threatened or Declining Habitats list. Posidonia beds are protected under Annex I of the EU Habitats Directive. This data product should be considered a work in progress and is not an official product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>735ea8c9-5bb7-48a2-a41d-57e521f97ae8</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Areal Extent of Live Hard Coral (Essential Ocean Variable)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>This layer shows the current known extent of Live Hard Coral in European waters, collated by EMODnet Seabed Habitats. Lophelia pertusa and Coral gardens are both on the OSPAR List of threatened and/or declining species and habitats. The relevant habitats were extracted from the library of maps on the EMODnet Seabed Habitats portal and collated into one standardised shapefile. This data product should be considered a work in progress and is not an official product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>913a0ee4-45d7-45aa-8de2-3d31af0f7c0e</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Areal Extent of Macroalgal Canopy (Essential Ocean Variable)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Habitats and biotopes</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>geoscientificInformation</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>biota</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>oceans</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>This layer shows the current known extent of macroalgal forests in European waters, collated by EMODnet Seabed Habitats. Kelp and fucoid brown algae are the dominant species that comprise macroalgal forests. The relevant habitats were extracted from the library of maps on the EMODnet Seabed Habitats portal and collated into one standardised shapefile.  This data product should be considered a work in progress and is not an official product.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>5f239d08b31d32c7c22efbe51f5aba7fe14b7332</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>Gridded abundances of marine species (10 year average)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>features</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Species_gridded_abundances_10year</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject />
      <dc:format />
      <dct:abstract>This dataproduct consists of a set of gridded map layers showing the average abundance of different species of species groups for different time windows (seasonal, annual or multi-annual as appropriate) using spatial modelling.
They cover a wide taxonomic range, from the smallest organisms (e.g. diatoms, flagellates) to the largest ones (e.g. fish, birds, reptiles, mammals), encompassing all trophic levels.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
    <csw:SummaryRecord xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:geonet="http://www.fao.org/geonetwork">
      <dc:identifier>93FEC453-DFEA-42C6-89C1-9F911E9A6C95</dc:identifier>
      <dc:title>EMODnet submarine landslide point  (1:100k)</dc:title>
      <dc:type>dataset</dc:type>
      <dc:subject>Submarine landslide, marine geology, geological events</dc:subject>
      <dc:subject>Downloadable Data</dc:subject>
      <dc:format>Shapefile</dc:format>
      <dct:abstract>Submarine landslides, detected on the seabed, outcropping or buried, mapped by various national and regional mapping projects and recovered in the literature. Points represent landslide areas smaller than 4 hectares. (for larger areas, see submarine landslides polygons layer) Note: blank areas do not necessarily correspond to no occurrence.</dct:abstract>
    </csw:SummaryRecord>
  </csw:SearchResults>
</csw:GetRecordsResponse>

